<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A late voyage to St. Kilda, the remotest of all the Hebrides, or the Western isles of Scotland with a history of the island, natural moral, and topographical : wherein is an account of their customes religion, fish, fowl, &amp;c. : as also a relation of a late impostor there, pretended to be sent by St. John Baptist / by M. Martin, gent.</title>
            <author>Martin, Martin, d. 1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 92 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52112</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M847</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12426586</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12426586</idno>
            <idno type="VID">199743</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52112)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199743)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 945:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A late voyage to St. Kilda, the remotest of all the Hebrides, or the Western isles of Scotland with a history of the island, natural moral, and topographical : wherein is an account of their customes religion, fish, fowl, &amp;c. : as also a relation of a late impostor there, pretended to be sent by St. John Baptist / by M. Martin, gent.</title>
                  <author>Martin, Martin, d. 1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 158, [2] p. : map  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for D. Brown and T. Goodwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Saint Kilda (Scotland) --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199743:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LATE VOYAGE TO St. KILDA, The <hi>Remoteſt</hi> of all the <hi>HEBRIDES,</hi> OR <hi>Weſtern</hi> Iſles of SCOTLAND. WITH A Hiſtory of the Iſland, Natural, Moral, and Topographical. Wherein is an Account of their Cuſtoms, Religion, Fiſh, Fowl, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As alſo a Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a late IMPOSTOR there, pretended to be Sent by St. <hi>John Baptiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> M. MARTIN, <hi>Gent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>D. Brown,</hi> and <hi>T. Goodwin:</hi> At the <hi>Black Swan</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar;</hi> and at the <hi>Queen's Head</hi> againſt St. <hi>Dunſtan's</hi> Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> MDCXCVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:199743:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199743:2"/>
            <p>A LATE VOYAGE TO <hi>St. Kilda,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:199743:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199743:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:199743:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199743:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>Charles Montague,</hi>
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>. Chancellor of His MAJESTY'S <hi>Exchequer,</hi> Preſident to the <hi>Royal Society</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE <hi>Royal Society</hi> (in which you ſo worthily at this time Preſide) having formerly done me the Honour to publiſh ſome of my Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in their Celebrated <hi>Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions,</hi> it has now encouraged me to preſume on your Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, and made me prefix Your Great Name to this little Eſſay.</p>
            <p>The World is in general ſo well acquainted with thoſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Endowments and great Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, for which our moſt Wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:199743:5"/>and Diſcerning Monarch ſo early raiſed You to the higheſt Places of Truſt and Dignity, that only theſe poor Iſlanders of whom I Write, ſeem to be unhappily excluded from the knowledge of thoſe many rare and excellent Virtues, which under Your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration do ſo ſignally Bleſs Mankind; of all which no One ſeems ſo neceſſary for me to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore, as that of Your extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Goodneſs; which, I hope, will incline You to accept of this plain and humble Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, as alſo to pardon the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt Humble and Obedient Servant, <hi>M. MARTIN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:199743:5"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>MEN are generally delighted with Novelty, and what is repreſented under that plauſible invitation ſeldom fails of meeting with acceptance. If we hear at any time a Deſcription of ſame remote Corner in the <hi>Indies</hi> Cried in our Streets, we preſently conclude we may have ſome Divertiſement in Reading of it; when in the mean time, there are a Thouſand things nearer us that may engage our thoughts to better purpoſes, and the knowledge of which may ſerve more to promote our true Intereſt, and the Hiſtory of Nature. It is a piece of weakneſs and folly merely to value things becauſe of their diſtance from the place where we are Born: Thus Men have Travelled far enough in the ſearch of Foreign Plants and Animals, and yet continue ſtrangers to thoſe produced in their own natural Climate. Therefore I preſume that this following Relation will not prove unprofitable or diſpleaſing, unleſs the great Advantages of Truth and unaffected
<pb facs="tcp:199743:6"/>plainneſs may do it a prejudice, in the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of ſuch as are more nice and childiſh than ſolid and judicious.</p>
            <p>The Ingenious Author of this Treatiſe is a Perſon whoſe Candor and Integrity guard him againſt all Affectation and Vanity; and his great deſire to propagate the Natural Hiſtory of the Iſles of <hi>Scotland,</hi> makes him relate, without any diſguiſe, the ſeveral particulars that fell under his accurate Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation. He was prompted by a generous Curioſity to undertake a Voyage through ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Iſles to St. <hi>Kilda</hi> (the particular account whereof you have in the following Treatiſe) and that in an open Boat, to the almoſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt hazard of his life, ſince the Seas and Tides in thoſe Rocky Iſlands are more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant and raging than in moſt other places. There is nothing related in the following Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, but what he vouches to be true, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from his own particular Obſervation, or elſe from the conſtant and harmonious Teſtimony that was given him by the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants; and they are a ſort of People ſo
<pb facs="tcp:199743:6"/>Plain, and ſo little inclined to Impoſe upon Mankind, that perhaps no place in the World at this day, knows ſuch Inſtances of true primitive Honour and Simplicity; a People who abhor lying Tricks and Artifices, as they do the moſt poiſonous Plants, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Animals.</p>
            <p>The Author, perhaps, might have put theſe Papers into the Hands of ſome who were capable of giving them the politeſt turns of Phraſe, and of making ſome pretty Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions upon ſeveral paſſages in them; but he thought the Intelligent and Philoſophick part of Mankind would value the Truth more in ſuch Accounts, than any thing that can be borrowed from Art, or the advantages of more refined Language; and ſuch do Contemplate the Books of Nature with ſo much diligence and application that they may admire the original ſpring of Power and Wiſdom, that firſt ſet Nature it ſelf in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and preſerves its regular courſe in all its wonderful and Various <hi>Phenomena;</hi> and therefore it may reaſonably be hoped,
<pb facs="tcp:199743:7"/>that the meanneſs of its dreſs will not be made uſe of as any conſiderable Objection againſt this preliminary Eſſay.</p>
            <p>He himſelf was Born in one of the moſt ſpacious and fertile Iſles in the <hi>Weſt</hi> of <hi>Scotland;</hi> and beſides his Liberal Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at the Univerſity, had the advantage of feeing Foreign Places, and the honour of Converſing with ſome of the <hi>Royal Society,</hi> who raiſed his natural Curioſity to ſurvey the Iſles of <hi>Scotland</hi> more exactly than any other; in proſecution of which deſign he has already brought along with him ſeveral curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Productions of Nature, both rare and beautiful in their kind, which were never ſeen nor known here before; and, perhaps, there be few that have the ſame advantages of doing it to purpoſe, he being generally acquainted with moſt of the better ſort, and nearly concerned in ſuch as would very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly encourage Endeavours of this and the like Nature.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A VOY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:199743:7"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. I.</label> THE Motives for the Voyage; Signs of a Storm; the Changes of the Wind; the Conſequence of their Change; the Flight of the Fowls; how ſerving the Natives as well as a Compaſs; a Fight betwixt Two <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe; the way the Inhabitants walk among the Rocks; the manner of Landing; the Number of Eggs conſum'd in Three Weeks; various Names of the Iſle; Latitude, Climate, Seaſons, Length and Breadth of it; the Bay; Force of the Sea; Four Arches, or Vaults; Chryſtal, how it grows; a Female Warrior's Houſe; Fountains; Marks on the Cattel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Fiſhes, Baits; <hi>Amphibia. P. 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:199743:8"/>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. II.</label> Of the inferior Iſles and Rocks, their Product. <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe, how Killed. A branch of the Officer's Salary, Stal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler-houſe, Pyramids. Policy of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants. An Earthquake. A Fountain. The taking away, or leaving the Eggs in the Neſts by the Inhabitants, advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or retards the hatching of the Fowls by the ſpace of Eighteen Days, ſooner or later. Our progreſs to <hi>Borera.</hi> Every <hi>Solan</hi> Gooſe catch'd, is preſently mark'd on the Foot by the Owner. Of Eddies. Tides. Land and Sea-Fowls, their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, various Properties, Seaſons for their coming, and going away: Their Prognoſticks of Winds, Storms, Calms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Barren Tribe of <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe. The <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe's Centinels. <hi>Fulmar</hi> Oyl, its properties. Eggs, their various Properties and Effects. <hi>p. 33.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:199743:8"/>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. III.</label> Of the Inhabitants. Their Pedigree: Completion: Strength: Diſeaſes: Cures: Plants: Religion: Notion of Spirits. Feſtivals: Anniverſary Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cade: Chappels: Crucifix: Lots: Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage: Baptiſm. Proprietor: Omer: Cubit. Envoy, his Salary, Entry. Steward's Retinue: His Reſidence: How far Limited. Tributary Cake. Mutton furniſhed by the Officer to the Steward every Sunday. Number of the Inhabitants: Their Kiln by turns. The Officer: His Precedence: Notion of Honour: The danger attending this Notion. Dexterity in Climbing. Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. Habit. Burials. Ale, how Brewed. Fowls preſerved. A Calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe conſumed by the Inhabitants laſt Tear. Five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Stone-Pyramids for ſeveral uſes. The Inhabitant's Food. Great lovers
<pb facs="tcp:199743:9"/>of Tobacco. Their Boat, how nicely divided. Fire-Penny: Pot-Penny. No Money uſed here. The Rock-Fowl: How preſented by a Lover to his Miſtreſs. The <hi>Miſtreſs-Stone.</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of all Foreign Objects. Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements. <hi>p. 69.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Account of one <hi>Roderick,</hi> ſuppoſed to have had Converſation with a Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Spirit, and pretending to be Sent by St. <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> with New Revelations and Diſcoveries. <hi>p. 135.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="map">
            <pb facs="tcp:199743:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199743:10"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199743:10"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199743:92"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>map of St. Kilda</figDesc>
                  <head>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Kilda</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199743:11"/>
            <head>A VOYAGE TO St. KILDA, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Motives for the Voyage; Signs of a Storm; the Changes of the Wind; the Conſequence of their Change; the Flight of the Fowls; how ſerving the Natives as well as a Compaſs; a Fight betwixt two <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe; the way the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants walk among the Rocks; the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of landing; the Number of Eggs conſum'd in Three Weeks; various names of the Iſle; Latitude, Climate,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:199743:12"/>Seaſons, Length and Breadth of it; the Bay; Force of the Sea; Four Arches or Vaults; Chryſtal, how it grows; a Female Warrior's Houſe; Fountains; Marks on the Cattel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Fiſhes, Baits; <hi>Amphibia.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE various Relations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> given by thoſe of the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Iſles, and Continent, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd me to a narrow Enquiry about it: For this End I applied my ſelf to the preſent Steward, who by his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, and the Products of the Iſland, which were brought to me, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a Natural Impulſe of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, form'd ſuch an Idea of it in my Mind, that I determin'd to ſatisfy my ſelf with the firſt Occaſion I had of going thither; it being never hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto deſcrib'd to any purpoſe; the Accounts which are given by <hi>Buchanan</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:199743:12"/>and Sir <hi>Robert Murray,</hi> being but Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations from Second and Third Hands, neither of them ever having the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of being upon the Place; which I attempted ſeveral times to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, but in vain; until laſt Summer, the Laird of <hi>Mack-Leod</hi> heartily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending the Care of the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of St. <hi>Kilda</hi> to Mr. <hi>John Campbel,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Harries,</hi> who accordingly went to St. <hi>Kilda.</hi> This Occaſion I chearfully embrac'd; and accordingly we embark'd at the Iſle <hi>Eſay</hi> in <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> the 29th. of <hi>May,</hi> at Six in the Afternoon, 1697. the Wind at <hi>S. E.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We ſet Sail with a gentle Breeze of Wind, bearing to the <hi>Weſtward,</hi> and were not well got out of the Harbour, when Mr. <hi>Campbell</hi> obſerving the White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Waves attended with an extraordinary Noiſe beating upon the Rocks, expreſs'd his Diſlike of it, as in thoſe Parts a never-failing Progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:199743:13"/>of an enſuing Storm; but the ſame appearing ſometimes in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, before exceſſive Heat, this was ſlighted by the Crew. But as we ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced about two Leagues further, upon the Coaſt of the Iſle <hi>Pabbay,</hi> the former Signs appearing more conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly, we were forc'd unanimouſly to conclude a Storm was approaching, which occaſion'd a Motion for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn; but the Wind and Ebb-Tide concurring, determin'd us to purſue our Voyage, in hopes to arrive at our deſired Harbour, before the Wind or Storm ſhould riſe, which we judged would not be ſuddenly: But our fond Imagination was not ſeconded with a good Event, as appears by the Sequel; for we had ſcarce ſail'd a League fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when the Wind inclin'd more <hi>Southerly,</hi> and alter'd our Meaſures; we endeavour'd by the help of our Oars to reach the <hi>Haw-sker Rocks,</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:199743:13"/>ſome Four Leagues to the <hi>South</hi>-Coaſt, which we were not able to effect, tho we conſum'd the Night in this vain ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation. By this time we are ſo far advanc'd in the Ocean, that after a ſecond Motion for our Return, it was not found practicable, eſpecially ſince we could not promiſe to fetch any Point of <hi>Scotland;</hi> this obliged us to make the beſt of our way for St. <hi>Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> though labouring under the Diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of Wind and Tide almoſt contrary to us. Our Crew became extremely fatigu'd and diſcouraged without ſight of Land for Sixteen Hours; at length one of our Number diſcovered ſeveral Tribes of the Fowls of St. <hi>Kilda</hi> flying, holding their Courſe <hi>Southerly</hi> of us, which (to ſome of our Crew) was a demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration we had loſt our Courſe, by the Violence of the Flood and Wind both concurring to carry us <hi>Northerly,</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:199743:14"/>though we ſteer'd by our Compaſs right <hi>Weſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Inhabitants of St. <hi>Kilda</hi> take their Meaſures from the Flight of thoſe Fowls, when the Heavens are not clear, as from a ſure Compaſs, Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience ſhewing that every Tribe of Fowls bends their Courſe to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Quarters, though out of ſight of the Iſle; this appeared clearly in our gradual Advances; and their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being compar'd, did exactly qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drate with our Compaſs. The Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants rely ſo much upon this Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vrtion, that they prefer it to the ſureſt Compaſs; but we begg'd their Pardon to differ from them, though at the ſame time we could not deny but their Rule was as certain as our Compaſs. While we were in this ſtate, one of our Number eſpi'd the Iſle <hi>Borera,</hi> near Three Leagues <hi>North</hi> of St. <hi>Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> which was then about Four Leagues
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:199743:14"/>to the <hi>South</hi> of us; this was a joyful Sight, and begot new Vigor in our Men, who being refreſh'd with Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, low'ring Maſt and Sail, rowed to a Miracle: While they were tugging at the Oars, we plied them with Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Aqua Vitae</hi> to ſupport them, whoſe borrow'd Spirits did ſo far waſte their own, that upon our Arrival at <hi>Borera,</hi> there was ſcarce one of our Crew able to manage Cable or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor: We arriv'd there, and put in under the hollow of an extraordinary high Rock, to the <hi>North</hi> of this Iſle, which was all covered with a prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Number of <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe hatching in their Neſts; the Heavens were dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by thoſe flying above our heads; their Excrements were in ſuch quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that they gave a Tincture to the Sea, and at the ſame time ſullied out Boat and Cloaths: Two of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed the Truth of what has been
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:199743:15"/>frequently reported of their ſtealing from one another Graſs wherewith to make their Neſts, by affording us the following and very agreeable diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and 'twas thus; One of them finding his Neighbour's Neſt without the Fowl, lays hold upon the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, and ſteals of it as much Graſs as he could conveniently carry, taking his flight towards the Ocean; from thence he returns after a ſhort turn, as if he had made a foreign Purchaſe, but it does not paſs for ſuch, as Fate would have it; for the Owner diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the fact, before this Thief got out of ſight, and being too nimble for his cunning, waits his return, all arm'd with fury, engages him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately; this bloody Battel was fought above our heads, and proved fatal to the Thief, who fell dead ſo near our Boat, that our Men took him up, and preſently Dreſs'd and Eat
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:199743:15"/>him; which they reckoned as an Omen and Prognoſtick of good Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in this Voyage.</p>
               <p>We propoſed to be at St. <hi>Kilda</hi> next day, but our expectation was fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a violent Storm, which did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt drive us to the Ocean; where we had incurred no ſmall riſque, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no ways fitted for it; our Men laid aſide all hopes of life, being poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with the belief that all this Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune proceeded from the Impoſtor (of whom hereafter) who they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved had employed the Devil to raiſe this extraordinary Storm againſt Mr. <hi>Campbel,</hi> Miniſter, who was to counteract him. All our Arguments, whether from Natural Reaſon, or the Providence of God, were not of force enough to perſuade them to the contrary, until it pleaſed <hi>God</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand a Calm the day following, which was the Firſt of <hi>June,</hi> and then
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:199743:16"/>we rowed to St. <hi>Kilda;</hi> as we came cloſe upon the Rocks, ſome of the Inhabitants, who were then employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſetting their Gins, welcomed us with a <hi>God ſave you,</hi> their uſual Saluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, admiring to ſee us get thither contrary to Wind and Tide; they were walking unconcernedly on the ſide of this prodigious high Rock, at the ſame time keeping pace with our Boat, to my great admiration, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that I was quickly obliged to turn away mine Eyes, leſt I ſhould have had the unpleaſant ſpectacle of ſome of them tumbling down into the Sea; but they themſelves had no ſuch fears, for hey outrun our Boat to the Town, from thence they brought the Steward and all the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of both Sexes to receive us; we approached the outmoſt part of the low Rock, called the <hi>Saddle;</hi> a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of the Inhabitants were mounted
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:199743:16"/>upon it, having on their Feet the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al dreſs on ſuch occaſions, <hi>i. e.</hi> Socks of old Rags ſowed with Feathers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Thread; our Boat being come pretty near, it was kept off this Rock with long Poles; ſome of their number coming by Pairs into the Sea received Mr. <hi>Campbel</hi> and me upon their Shoulders and carried us to Land, where we were received with all the demonſtrations of joy and kindneſs they were able to expreſs; the Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor endeavouring to outdo his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and placing himſelf always in the front of our Attendants, diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered his Hypocriſy, of which an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count ſhall be given in the Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. All of us walking together to the little Village where there was a Lodging prepared for us, furniſhed with Beds of Straw, and according to the ancient Cuſtom of the place, the Officer, who preſides over them
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:199743:17"/>(in the Steward's abſence) ſummoned the Inhabitants, who by concert agreed upon a daily Maintenance for us, as, Bread, Butter, Cheeſe, Mutton, Fowls, Eggs, alſo Fire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all which was to be given in at our Lodging. Twice every day; this was done in the moſt regular manner, each Family by turns paying their Quota proportionably to their Lands. I remember the allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance fot each Man <hi>per diem,</hi> beſide a Barley Cake, was Eighteen of the Eggs laid by the Fowl called by them <hi>Lavy,</hi> and a greater Number of the leſſer Eggs, as they differed in Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the largeſt of theſe Eggs is near in bigneſs to that of a Gooſe, the reſt of the Eggs gradually of a leſſer Size.</p>
               <p>We had the curioſity after Three Weeks reſidence, to make a Calcule of the number of Eggs beſtowed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe of our Boat, and the <hi>Stewart's Birlin,</hi> or <hi>Galley,</hi> the whole amounted
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:199743:17"/>to Sixteen thouſand Eggs; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt the Inhabitants, who were tripple our Number, conſumed many more Eggs and Fowls than we could. From this it is eaſy to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that a vaſt number of Fowls muſt reſort here all Summer, which is yet the more probable if it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that every Fowl lays but one Egg at a time, if allowed to hatch.</p>
               <p>The Inhabitants live together in a little Vilage, which carries all the ſigns of an extream Poverty; the Houſes are of a low form, having all the Doors to the <hi>North-Eaſt,</hi> both on purpoſe to ſecure them from the ſhocks of the Tempeſt of the <hi>South-Weſt</hi> Winds. The Walls of their Houſes are rudely built of Stone, the ſhort Couples joining at the ends of the Roof, upon whoſe ſides ſmall ribs of Wood are laid, theſe being covered with Straw; the whole ſecured by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:199743:18"/>Ropes made of twiſted Heather, the extremity of which on each ſide is poiſed with Stone to preſerve the Thatch from being blown away by the Winds. This little Village is ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a Valley ſurrounded with Four Mountains, which ſerve as ſo many Ramparts of defence, and are Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phitheatres, from whence a fair pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Ocean and Iſles is to be ſeen in a fair day.</p>
               <p>This Iſle is by the Inhabitants called <hi>Hirt,</hi> and likewiſe by all the Weſtern Iſlanders; <hi>Buchanan</hi> calls it <hi>Hirta;</hi> Sir <hi>John Narbrough,</hi> and all Seamen, call it St. <hi>Kilda;</hi> and in Sea Maps St. <hi>Kilder,</hi> particularly in a <hi>Dutch</hi> Sea Map from <hi>Ireland</hi> to <hi>Zeland,</hi> publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Amſterdam</hi> by <hi>Peter Goas</hi> in the Year 1663, wherein the Iſle of St. <hi>Kilda</hi> is placed due <hi>Weſt</hi> betwixt Fifty and Sixty Miles from the middle of the <hi>Lewis,</hi> and the Iſle anſwers di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:199743:18"/>to the Fifty Eighth Degree of <hi>Northern</hi> Latitude, as marked upon the ends of the Map, and from it lies <hi>Rokol,</hi> a ſmall Rock Sixty Leagues to the <hi>Weſtward</hi> of St. <hi>Kilda;</hi> the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of this place call it <hi>Rokabarra;</hi> this Map contains the ſoundings of ſome places near St. <hi>Kilda;</hi> theſe not exceeding Twenty or Thirty Fathom, it contains only the larger Iſle, and a part of the Leſſer Iſles; this Iſland is alſo called St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> by a Company of <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who loſt their Ship at <hi>Rokol</hi> in the Year 1686, which they Nam'd to the Inhabitants of St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> whoſe Latitude is Fifty ſeven Degrees and Three Minutes.</p>
               <p>The Air here is ſharp and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome; the Hills are often covered with ambient White Miſts, which in Winter are Forerunners of Snow, if they continue on the Tops of the Hills; and in Summer, if only on the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:199743:19"/>Tops of the Hills, they prognoſticate Rain; and when they deſcend to the Valleys it is a Prognoſtick of exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Heat. The Night here about the time of the Summer Solſtice ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds not an Hour in length, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if the Seaſon is fair, then the Sun diſappears but for a ſhort ſpace, the Reflex from the Sea being all the time viſible; the Harveſt and Winter are liable to great Winds and Rain, the <hi>South-Weſt</hi> Wind annoying them more than any other; it is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerved to blow from the <hi>Weſt</hi> for the moſt part of, if not all <hi>July.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Kilda</hi> is Two Miles long from <hi>Eaſt</hi> to <hi>Weſt;</hi> from <hi>South</hi> to <hi>North</hi> One Mile in breadth; Five Miles in Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference, and is naturally fenc'd with one continued Face of a Rock of great height, except a part of the Bay, which lies to the <hi>South-Eaſt,</hi> and is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally well fenced with a raging Sea:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:199743:19"/>This Bay is one Half Mile in length, and another in breadth; it is not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary for any Veſſels to Anchor with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Bay, in caſe of a Storm, for this might endanger them; therefore they drop Anchor without at the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, judging it the ſecureſt place: The only place for landing here, is on the <hi>North</hi> ſide of this Bay, upon a Rock with a little declination, which is ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, being cloathed with ſeveral ſorts of Sea-Weeds; theſe, together with a raging Sea, render the Place more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acceſſible, it being ſeldom without a raging Sea, except under favour of a Neap Tide, a <hi>North-Eaſt</hi> or <hi>Weſt</hi> Wind, or with a perfect Calm; when theſe Circumſtances concur, the <hi>Birlin</hi> or Boat is brought to the ſide of the Rock, upon which all the Inhabitants of both Sexes are ready to join their united Force to hale her through this Rock, having for this end a Rope faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:199743:20"/>to the Fore-part; a competent Number of them are alſo employed on each ſide; both theſe are determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by a Cryer, who is employed on purpoſe to warn them all at the ſame Minute, and he ceaſes when he finds it convenient to give them a breathing.</p>
               <p>At the Head of the Bay there's a plain Sand, which is only to be ſeen in Summer, the Winter-Sea waſhing it all off the Stones; there is no landing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this place with ſafety, which the <hi>Steward</hi> has learn'd to his Coſt. There is a little Bay on the <hi>Weſt</hi> ſide of this Iſle, all fac'd with an Iron-colour'd Rock; ſome Veſſels take ſhelter here, when the Wind is at <hi>South</hi> or <hi>North-Eaſt;</hi> there is a place of the Rock here on the <hi>South</hi>-ſide the Rivulet, where you may land, if a Neap-Tide or Calm offer. The Sea is very impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous every where about this Iſle; they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:199743:20"/>ſhewed me big Stones which were late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly removed out of their place, and caſt into the Gallies Dock; I meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſome of them which were in length ſeven, others eight Foot, and three or four broad.</p>
               <p>There is a little old ruinous Fort on the <hi>South</hi> Part of the <hi>South-Eaſt</hi> Bay, called the <hi>Down.</hi> It is evident from what hath been already ſaid, that this Place may be reckoned among the ſtrongeſt Forts (whether Natural or Artificial) in the World; Nature has provided the Place with ſtore of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition for acting on the Defenſive; that is, a heap of looſe Stones in the Top of the Hill <hi>Oterveaul,</hi> directly above the Landing-place; it is very eaſy to diſcharge Vollies of this Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition directly upon the place of Landing, and that from a great height almoſt Perpendicular; this I my ſelf had occaſion to demonſtrate, having
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:199743:21"/>for my Diverſion put it in practice, to the great ſatisfaction of the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, to whom this Defence never oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr'd hitherto. They are reſolved to make uſe of this for the future, to keep off the Lowlanders, againſt whom of late they have conceived Prejudices. A few hands may be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of reſiſting ſome hundreds, if the above-mentioned Weapons be but made uſe of. Thoſe Four Mountains are fac'd on that ſide which regards the Sea, with Rocks of extraordinary height; the Hill <hi>Conagir</hi> on the <hi>North</hi> ſide, is about Two hundred Fathom height, perpendicularly above the Sea.</p>
               <p>There are round this Iſle Four <hi>Arches</hi> or <hi>Vaults,</hi> through which the Sea paſſes, as doth the Day-light from either ſide, which is viſible to any, though at a good diſtance; ſome of them repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting a large Gate: Two of theſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:199743:21"/>look to the <hi>South,</hi> and two <hi>North-Weſt;</hi> that on the Point of the <hi>Weſt</hi> Bay is ſix Fathom high above Water, four in breadth, fifty Paces in length, the top two Fathom thick, and very ſtrong, the Cattle feeding upon it.</p>
               <p>There are ſeveral Veins of different Stone to be ſeen in the Rocks of the <hi>South-Eaſt</hi> Bay; upon the <hi>North</hi> ſide of this Rock is one as it were cut out by Nature, reſembling a Tarras-Walk. The Chryſtal grows under the Rock at the Landing-place; this Rock muſt be pierc'd a Foot or two deep, before the Chryſtal can be had from the Bed of Sand where it lies; the Water at the bottom is of a black Colour; the lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt Piece is not above four Inches long, and about two in Diameter, each Piece Sexangular.</p>
               <p>Upon the <hi>Weſt</hi> ſide of this Iſle there is a Valley with a Declination towards the Sea, having a Rivulet running
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:199743:22"/>through the middle of it, on each ſide of which is an Aſcent of half a Mile; all which Piece of Ground is call'd by the Inhabitants, The Female Warrior's <hi>Glen:</hi> This <hi>Amazon</hi> is fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in their Traditions: Her Houſe or Dairy of Stone is yet extant; ſome of the Inhabitants dwell in it all Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, though it be ſome Hundred Years old; the whole is built of Stone, without any Wood, Lime, Earth, or Mortar to cement it, and is built in form of a Circle Pyramid-wiſe towards the Top, having a Vent in it, the Fire being always in the Centre of the Floor; the Stones are long and thin, which ſupplies the defect of Wood: The Body of this Houſe contains not above Nine Perſons ſitting; there are three Beds or low Vaults that go off the ſide of the Wall, a Pillar betwixt each Bed, which contains five Men apiece; at the Entry to one of theſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:199743:22"/>low Vaults is a Stone ſtanding upon one end fix'd; upon this they ſay ſhe ordinarily laid her Helmet; there are two Stones on the other ſide, upon which ſhe is reported to have laid her Sword: She is ſaid to have been much addicted to Hunting, and that in her time all the ſpace betwixt this Iſle and that of <hi>Harries,</hi> was one continued Tract of Dry Land. There was ſome years ago a Pair of large Deers-horns found in the top of <hi>Oterveaul</hi> Hill, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a Foot under Ground; and there was likewiſe a Wooden Diſh full of Deer's Greaſe found in the ſame Hill under Ground. 'Tis alſo ſaid of this Warrior, that ſhe let looſe her Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hounds after the Deer in St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> making their Courſe towards the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite Iſles. There are ſeveral Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this famous <hi>Amazon,</hi> with which I will not further trouble the Reader.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:199743:23"/>
               <p>In this Iſle there are plenty of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Fountains or Springs; That near the Female Warrior's Houſe is reputed to be the beſt, the Name of it, <hi>Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bir-nim buey,</hi> importing no leſs than the Well of Qualities or Virtues; it runneth from <hi>Eaſt</hi> to <hi>Weſt,</hi> being ſixty Paces Aſcent above the Sea: I drank of it twice, an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Quart at each time; it is very clear, exceeding cold, light, and diuretick; I was not able to hold my hands in it above a few Minutes, in regard of its Coldneſs; the Inhabitants of <hi>Harries</hi> find it ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual againſt Windy-Chollicks, Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, Head-aches; this Well hath a Cover of Stone.</p>
               <p>There is a very large Well near the Town, called St. <hi>Kilder</hi>'s Well; from which the Iſland is ſuppos'd to derive its Name; this Water is not inferior to that above-mentioned; it runneth to the <hi>South-Eaſt</hi> from the <hi>North-Weſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:199743:23"/>
               <p>There is another Well within half a Mile of this, nam'd after one <hi>Conirdan,</hi> an hundred Paces above the Sea, and runneth from <hi>North-Weſt</hi> towards the <hi>South-Eaſt,</hi> having a Stone Cover.</p>
               <p>Within twelve Paces of this is a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and excellent Fountain, which thoſe of <hi>Harries</hi> and St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> will needs call by the Author's Name, and were then reſolved to give it a Cover of Stone, ſuch as is above deſcrib'd.</p>
               <p>There is a celebrated Well iſſuing out of the Face of a Rock on the <hi>North</hi>-ſide of the <hi>Eaſt</hi> Bay, called by the Inhabitants and others, <hi>The Well of Youth,</hi> but is only acceſſible by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, no Stranger daring to climb the ſteep Rock; the Water of it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, as it falls, into the Sea; it runs towards the <hi>South-Eaſt.</hi> The Taſte of the Water of thoſe Wells was ſo pleaſant, that for ſeveral Weeks after, the beſt Fountains in the adjacent Iſles
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:199743:24"/>did not reliſh with me. There is a Rivulet runneth cloſe by the Town, and another larger beyond <hi>Kilder</hi>'s Well; this laſt ſerves for waſhing Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen, which it doth as well without Soap, as other Water does with it; of this we had Experience, which was a Confirmation of what had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to us concerning this Water: We ſearched if in the Brinks we could diſcover any Fullers-Earth, but found none; we diſcovered ſome Pieces of Iron-Ore in ſeveral places of it; this Rivulet drops from the Moſſy Ground in the top of the Hills.</p>
               <p>The whole Iſland is one hard Rock, form'd into four high Mountains, three of which are in the middle; all thinly covered with black or brown Earth, not above a Foot, ſome places half a foot deep, except the top of the Hills, where it is above three Foot deep, and affords them good Turf;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:199743:24"/>the Graſs is very ſhort but kindly, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing plenty of Milk; the number of Sheep commonly maintained in St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> and the two adjacent Iſles, does not exceed Two thouſand, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally they are Speckled, ſome White, ſome Philamort, and are of an ordinary ſize; they do not reſemble Goats in any thing, as <hi>Buchanan</hi> was informed, except in their Horns, which are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary large, particularly thoſe in the leſſer Iſles.</p>
               <p>The number of Horſes exceeds not Eighteen, all of a Red Colour, very low, and ſmooth Skinn'd, being only employed in carrying their Turf and Corn, and at the Anniverſary Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cade, of which hereafter. The Cows that are about Ninety Head, ſmall and great, all of them having their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads White and Black, which is diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable at a great diſtance, are of a low ſtature, but fat and ſweet Beef; the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:199743:25"/>Dogs, Cats, and all the Sea-Fowls of this Iſle are Speckled.</p>
               <p>The Soil is very grateful to the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer, producing ordinarily Sixteen, Eighteen, or Twenty Fold ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times; their Grain is only <hi>Bear,</hi> and ſome Oats; the Barley is the largeſt produced in all the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Iſles; they uſe no Plough but a kind of crooked Spade; their Harrows are of Wood, as are the Teeth in the front alſo, and all the reſt ſupplied only with long tangles of Sea-ware tied to the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row by the ſmall ends; the Roots hanging looſe behind, ſcatter the clods broken by the Wooden Teeth; this they are forced to uſe for want of Wood. Their Arable Land is very nicely parted into Ten Diviſions, and theſe into Subdiviſions, each Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion diſtinguiſhed by the Name of ſome Deceaſed Man or Woman, who were Natives of the Place; there is
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:199743:25"/>one ſpot called <hi>Multa Terra,</hi> another <hi>Multus Agris.</hi> The chief ingredient in their Compoſts is Aſhes of Turf mixed with Straw; with theſe they mix their Urine, which by experience they find to have much of the Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Nitre; they do not preſerve it in quantities as elſewhere, but convey it immediately from the Fountain to the Aſhes, which by daily practice they find moſt advantageous; they join alſo the Bones, Wings, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trails of their Sea-Fowls to their Straw; they Sow very thick, and have a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable growth; they pluck all their <hi>Bear</hi> by the Roots in handfuls, both for the ſake of their Houſes, which they thatch with it, and their Cows which they take in during the Winter; the Corn produced by this Compoſt is perfectly free of any kind of Weeds; it produces much Sorrel where the Compoſt reaches.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:199743:26"/>
               <p>The Coaſt of St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> and the leſſer Iſles, are plentifully furniſhed with variety of Fiſhes, as Cod, Ling, Mackarell, Congars, Braziers, Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, Graylords, Sythes; theſe laſt two are the ſame kind, only differing in bigneſs, ſome call them Black Mouths; they are large as any Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and ſomewhat longer; there are alſo Laiths, Podloes, Herring, and many more; moſt of theſe are Fiſhed by the Inhabitants upon the Rock, for they have neither Nets nor long Lines. Their common Bait is the Lympets or <hi>Patellae,</hi> being par-boil'd; they uſe likewiſe the Fowl called by them Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, its Fleſh raw, which the Fiſh near the leſſer Iſles catch greedily; ſometimes they uſe the Bowger's fleſh, and the Lympets <hi>Patellae</hi> at the ſame time upon one Hook, and this proves ſucceſsful alſo. In the Month of <hi>July</hi> a conſiderable quantity of Mackarell
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:199743:26"/>run themſelves aſhoar, but always with a Spring-Tide. The <hi>Amphibia</hi> ſeen here, are the Otters and Seals; this latter the Inhabitants reckon very good Meat; there is no ſort of Trees, no, not the leaſt Shrub grows here, nor ever a Bee ſeen at any time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:199743:27"/>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:199743:27"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the inferior Iſles and Rocks, their Product. <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe, how Killed. A branch of the Officer's Salary, Stal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler-houſe, Pyramids. Policy of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants. An Earthquake. A Fountain. The taking away, or leaving the Eggs in the Neſts by the Inhabitants, advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or retards the hatching of the Fowls by the ſpace of Eighteen Days, ſooner or later. Our progreſs to <hi>Borera.</hi> Every <hi>Solan</hi> Gooſe catch'd, is preſently mark'd on the Foot by the Owner. Of Eddies. Tides. Land and Sea-Fowls, their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, various Properties, Seaſons for their coming, and going away: Their Prognoſticks of Winds, Storms, Calms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Barren Tribe of <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:199743:28"/>The <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe's Centinels. <hi>Fulmar</hi> Oyl, its properties. Eggs, their vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Properties and Effects.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>LEVINIS,</hi> a Rock about Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Paces high, and Thirty in circumference, narrower at the top; it ſtands about half a League to the <hi>South-Eaſt</hi> Bay, and is not covered with any kind of Earth or Graſs; it hath a Spring of Freſh Water iſſuing out at the ſide; this Rock, by an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Cuſtom, belongs to the Galley's Crew, but the above-mentioned allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance diſpoſes them to undervalue it. Betwixt the <hi>Weſt</hi> point of St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> and the Iſle <hi>Soa,</hi> is the famous Rock <hi>Stackdonn, i. e.</hi> as much, in their Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, as a <hi>Miſchievous Rock,</hi> for it hath prov'd ſo to ſome of their Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, who periſhed in attempting to climb it; it is much of the Form and Height of a Steeple; there is a very
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:199743:28"/>great dexterity, and it is reckoned no ſmall gallantry to climb this Rock, eſpecially that part of it called the <hi>Thumb,</hi> which is ſo little, that of all the Parts of a Man's Body, the Thumb only can lay hold on it, and that muſt be only for the ſpace of one Minute; during which time his Feet have no ſupport, nor any part of his Body touch the Stone, except the Thumb, at which Minute he muſt jump by the help of his Thumb, and the Agility of his Body concurring to raiſe him higher at the ſame time, to a ſharp point of the Rock, which when he has got hold of, puts him above danger, and having a Rope about his Middle, that he caſts down to the Boat, by the help of which he carries up as many Perſons as are deſigned for Fowl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at this time; the Foreman, or Principal Climber has the Reward of Four Fowls beſtowed upon him above
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:199743:29"/>his proportion; and, perhaps, one might think Four thouſand too little to compenſate ſo great a danger as this Man incurs; he has this advantage by it, that he is Recorded among their greateſt Heroes; as are all the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men who lead the Van in getting up this <hi>Miſchievous Rock.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Within Piſtol ſhot from this place is the Iſle <hi>Soa,</hi> a Mile and an half in circumference, but contracted narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er toward the top, being a full half Mile in difficult Aſcent all round, moſt of it bare Rock, ſome parts of it covered with Graſs, but dangerous to aſcend; the Landing is alſo very hazardous, both in regard of the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Sea, and the Rock that muſt be climb'd; yet the Inhabitants are accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to carry Burthens both up it and down, and of this I was once a Witneſs. There is ſcarce any Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here, except in one place, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:199743:29"/>that under favour of a <hi>Weſt</hi> Wind and Neap-Tide; the Waves upon the Rock diſcover when it is acceſſible; if they appear White from St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> the Inhabitants do not ſo much as offer to launch out their Boat, in order to Land in <hi>Soa,</hi> or any other Iſle or Rock, though their Lives were at the ſtake: This little Iſle is furniſhed with an excellent Spring; the Graſs, being very ſweet, Feeds Five hundred Sheep, each of them having generally Two or Three Lambs at a Birth, and every Lamb being ſo fruitful, that it brings forth a Lamb before it ſelf is a Year old. The ſame is alſo obſerved of Lambs in the little Iſles adjacent to the Iſles of <hi>Harries</hi> and <hi>North-Wiſt.</hi> The Sheep in this Iſle <hi>Soa</hi> are never Milk'd, which diſpoſes them to be the more prolifick: There are none to catch them but the Inhabitants, whom I have ſeen purſue the Sheep nimbly
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:199743:30"/>down the ſteep deſcent, with as great freedom as if it had been a plain Field.</p>
               <p>This Iſle abounds with infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Fowls, as Fulmar, Lavy, Falk, Bowger, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There was a Cock-boat ſome Two years ago came from a Ship for Water, being favoured by a perfect Calm; the Men diſcerned an infinite number of Eggs upon the Rocks, which charm'd them to venture near the place, and at laſt purchaſed a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent number of them; ſo careful was one of the Seamen as to put them into his Breeches, which he put off on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for this uſe; ſome of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of St. <hi>Kilda</hi> happened to be in the Iſle that day; a parcel of them were Spectators of this diverſion, and were offended at it, being done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their conſent, therefore they devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed an Expedient, which at once robb'd
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:199743:30"/>the Seamen of their Eggs and Breeches; and 'twas thus: They found a few looſe Stones in the Superficies of the Rock, ſome of which they let fall down perpendicularly above the Seamen, the terror of which obliged them quickly to remove, abandoning both Breeches and Eggs for their ſafety; and thoſe Tarpawlin Breeches were no ſmall Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament there, where all wore girded Plaids.</p>
               <p>About Two Leagues and a half to the <hi>North</hi> of St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> is the Rock <hi>Stack-Ly,</hi> Two hundred Paces in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference, and of a great heigth, being a perfect Triangle turning to a point at the top; it is viſible above Twenty Leagues diſtant in a fair day, and appears Blew; there is no Graſs nor Earth to cover it, and it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly White with <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe ſitting on and about it. One would think it next to impoſſible to climb this
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:199743:31"/>Rock, which I expreſs'd, being very cloſe by it; but the Inhabitants aſſured me it was practicable, and to convince me of the truth of it, they bid me look up near the top, where I perceived a Stone Pyramid-houſe, which the Inhabitants Built for Lodging themſelves in it in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> at which time the Seaſon proves inconſtant there; this obliges the Inhabitants in point of prudence to ſend a competent number of them to whoſe ſhare the Lots fall; theſe are to Land in this Rock ſome days before the time at which the <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe uſe to take Wing, and if they neglected this piece or foreſight, one Windy day might diſappoint them of Five, Six, or Seven thouſand <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe, this Rock affording no leſs yearly; and they are ſo very numerous here, that they cannot be divided with reſpect to their Lands, as elſewhere; therefore this is the reaſon why they ſend here
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:199743:31"/>by Lots, and thoſe who are ſent act for the publick Intereſt, and when they have knock'd on the head all that may be reached, they then carry them to a ſharp Point, called the <hi>Caſting-Point,</hi> from whence they throw them into the Sea, (the heighth being ſuch that they dare not throw them in, but near the Boat) until the Boatmen cry, <hi>Enough;</hi> leſt the Sea, which has a ſtrong Current there ſhould carry them off, as it does ſometimes, if too many are thrown down at once; and ſo by degrees getting all in, they return home; and after their Arrival every Man has his ſhare proportionable to his Lands, and what remains below the number Ten, is due to the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer as a branch of his yearly Salary. In this Rock the <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe are allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Hatch their firſt Eggs, but it is not ſo in the Rocks next to be descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed; and that for this reaſon, That if
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:199743:32"/>all were allowed to Hatch at the ſame time, the loſs of the product in one Rock would at the ſame time prove the loſs of all the reſt, ſince all would take Wing almoſt at once.</p>
               <p>The Iſle <hi>Borera</hi> lies near half a League from <hi>Stack-Ly,</hi> to the <hi>North-Eaſt</hi> of it, being in circumference One Mile and an half; it Feeds about Four hundred Sheep <hi>per Annum,</hi> and would Feed more, did not the <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe pluck a large ſhare of the Graſs for their Neſts.</p>
               <p>This Iſle is very high and all Rock, being inacceſſible except in a Calm, and there is only one place for Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, looking to the <hi>South:</hi> In the <hi>Weſt</hi> end of this Iſle is <hi>Stallir-Houſe,</hi> which is much larger than that of the Female Warrior in St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> but of the ſame Model in all reſpects; it is all Green without like a little Hill; the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants there have a Tradition that it was
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:199743:32"/>Built by one <hi>Stallir,</hi> who was a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Hermit of St. <hi>Kilda;</hi> and had he Travelled the Univerſe he could ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have found a more Solitary place for a Monaſtick Life.</p>
               <p>There are about Forty Stone Pyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mids in this Iſle, for drying and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving their Fowls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe little Houſes are all of looſe Stones, and ſeen at ſome diſtance; there is alſo here a very ſurprizing number of Fowls, the Graſs as well as the Rocks filled with them. The <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe poſſeſs it for the moſt part; they are always Maſters where-ever they come, and have already baniſhed ſeveral Species of Fowls from this Iſle.</p>
               <p>There was an Earthquake here in the Year 1686, which laſted but a few Minutes; it was very amazing to the poor People, who never felt any ſuch Commotion before, or ſince.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:199743:33"/>
               <p>To the <hi>Weſt</hi> of <hi>Borera</hi> lies the Rock <hi>Stack-Narmin,</hi> within Piſtol-Shot; this Rock is Half a Mile in circumference, and is as inacceſſible as any the above-mentioned; there is a poſſibility of Landing only in two places, and that but in a perfect Calm neither, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Landing the Danger in Climbing it is very great. The Rock has not any Earth or Graſs to cover it, and hath a Fountain of good Water iſſuing out above the middle of it, which run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <hi>Eaſterly:</hi> This Rock abounds with <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe and other Fowls; here are ſeveral Stone Pyramids, as well for Lodging the Inhabitants that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Seaſons of the <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe, as for thoſe that preſerve and dry them and other Fowls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Sea riſes and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges extraordinarily upon this Rock: We had the curioſity, being invited by a fair day, to viſit it for pleaſure, but it was very hazardous to us; the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:199743:33"/>Waves from under our Boat rebound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from off the Rock, and mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over our Heads wet us all, ſo that we durſt not venture to Land, though Men with Ropes were ſent before us; and we thought it hazard great enough to be near this Rock; the Wind blew freſh, ſo that we had much difficulty to fetch St. <hi>Kilda</hi> again; I remember they brought 800 of the preceeding year's <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe dried in their Pyramids; after our Landing, the Geeſe being caſt together in one heap upon the Ground, the Owners fell to ſhare out each Man his own, at which I was a little ſurpriſed, they being all of a Tribe; but having found upon Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that every Gooſe carried a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Mark on the Foot, peculiar to the Owner, I was then ſatisfied in this piece of ſingularity.</p>
               <p>There is a violent Current, whether Ebb or Flood, upon all the Coaſts
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:199743:34"/>of St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> leſſer Iſles and Rocks. It is obſerved to be more impetuous with Spring than Neap Tides; there are Eddies on all the Coaſts, except at a ſharp Point where the Tides keep their due courſe; the Ebb <hi>Southerly,</hi> and Flood <hi>Northerly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>S. E.</hi> Moon cauſeth high Tide; the Spring-Tides are always at the Full and New Moon; the two days following they are higher, and from that time de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe until the increaſe of the Moon again, with which it riſes gradually till the ſecond after the Full Moon. This Obſervation the Seamen find to hold true betwixt the <hi>Mule</hi> of <hi>Kantyre,</hi> and the <hi>Farrow Head</hi> in <hi>Strathnaver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Land-Fowls produced here are Hawks extraordinary good, Eagles, Plovers, Crows, Wrens, Stone-Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, Craker, Cuckoo; this laſt being very rarely ſeen here, and that upon extraordinary Occaſions, ſuch as the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:199743:34"/>Death of the Proprietor <hi>Mack-Leod,</hi> the Steward's Death, or the Arrival of ſome Notable Stranger. I was not able to forbear laughing at this Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as founded upon no reaſon but fancy; which I no ſooner expreſs'd, than the Inhabitants wondred at my Incredulity, ſaying, that all their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors for a <hi>Series</hi> of ſeveral Ages had remarked this Obſervation to prove true, and for a further confirmation, appealed to the preſent Steward, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he had not known this Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to have been true, both in his own and his Father's time, who was alſo Steward before him; and after a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular enquiry upon the whole, he told me, that both in his own and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's life-time the truth of this Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation has been conſtantly believed, and that ſeveral of the Inhabitants now living have obſerved the Cuckoo to have appeared after the Death of the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:199743:35"/>two laſt Proprietors, and the two laſt Stewards, and alſo before the Arrival of Strangers ſeveral times; it was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of this Year before our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival, which they aſcribe to my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there, as the only Stranger; the Miniſter having been there before.</p>
               <p>The Sea-Fowls are, firſt, <hi>Gairfowl,</hi> being the ſtatelieſt, as well as the Largeſt of all the Fowls here, and above the Size of a <hi>Solan</hi> Gooſe, of a Black Colour, Red about the Eyes, a large White Spot under each Eye, a long broad Bill; ſtands ſtately, his whole Body erected, his Wings ſhort, he Fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not at all, lays his Egg upon the bare Rock, which, if taken away, he lays no more for that Year; he is <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mipes,</hi> or Whole-Footed, and has the Hatching Spot upon his Breaſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> a bare Spot from which the Feathers have fallen off with the heat in Hatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; his Egg is twice as big as that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:199743:35"/>of a <hi>Solan</hi> Gooſe, and is variouſly ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Black, Green, and Dark; he comes without regard to any Wind, appears the firſt of <hi>May,</hi> and goes away about the middle of <hi>June.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Solan</hi> Gooſe, as ſome imagine from the <hi>Iriſh</hi> word <hi>Sou'l-er,</hi> corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and adapted to the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, <hi>qui oculis irretortis è longinquo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicit praedam:</hi> It equals a Tame Gooſe in bigneſs; it is by meaſure from the tip of the Bill to the extremity of the Foot, Thirty four Inches long, and to the end of the Tail, Thirty nine; the Wings extended very long, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Seventy two Inches of diſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the extream tips; its Bill is long, ſtrait, of a dark Colour, a little crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the point; behind the Eyes the Skin of the ſide of the Head is bare of Feathers; the Ears of a mean Size; the Eyes Hazel-coloured; it hath Four Toes; the Feet and Legs Black as far
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:199743:36"/>as they are bare; the Plumage is like that of a Gooſe. The Colour of the Old ones is White all over, excepting the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream tips of the Wings, which are Black, and the top of the Head, which is Yellow, as ſome think the Effect of Age. The Young ones are of a dark brown Colour, turning White after they are a Year old; its Egg, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what leſs than that of a Land-Goofe, ſmall at each end, and caſts a thick ſcurf, and has little or no Yolk. The Inhabitants are accuſtomed to drink it raw, having from Experience found it to be very Pectoral, and Cephalick. The <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe Hatch by turns; when it returns from its Fiſhing, carries along with it Five or Six Herrings in its Gorget, all entire and undigeſted, upon whoſe arrival at the Neſt, the Hatching Fowl puts its Head in the Fiſher's Throat, and pulls out the Fiſh with its Bill as with a Pincer, and that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:199743:36"/>with very great noiſe; which I had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion frequently to obſerve. They continue to pluck Graſs for their Neſts from their coming in <hi>March</hi> till the Young Fowl is ready to Fly in <hi>Auguſt</hi> or <hi>September,</hi> according as the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants take of leave the Firſt or Second Eggs. It's remarkable of them, that they never pluck Graſs but on a Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy day; the reaſon of which I enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the Inhabitants, who ſaid, that a Windy day is the <hi>Solan</hi> Gooſe's Vacation from Fiſhing, and they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow it upon this Employment, which proves fatal to many of them; for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their fatigue they often fall aſleep, and the Inhabitants laying hold on this opportunity, are ready at hand to knock them on the Head; their Food is Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, Mackrels, and <hi>Syes; Engliſh</hi> Hooks are often found in the Stomachs both of Young and Old <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe, though there be none of this kind uſed <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:199743:37"/>than the Iſles Twenty Leagues diſtant; the Fiſh pulling away the Hooks in thoſe Iſles go to St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> or are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by the Old Geeſe thither; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the two the Reader is at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to judge.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe are always the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt ſign of Herrings, for where-ever the one is ſeen, the other is always not far off. There is a Tribe of Barren <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe which have no Neſts, and ſit upon the bare Rock; theſe are not the Young Fowls of an Year Old, whoſe dark Colour would ſoon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh them, but Old ones, in all things like the reſt; theſe have a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, as it were, allotted to them, and are in a ſeparated ſtate from the others, having a Rock Two hundred Paces diſtant from all other; neither do they meddle with, or approach to thoſe Hatching, or any other Fowls; they Sympathize and Fiſh together;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:199743:37"/>this being told me by the Inhabitants, was afterwards confirmed to me ſeveral times by my own Obſervation.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe have always ſome of their Number that keep Centinel in the Night-time, and if they are ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized, (as it often happens) all that Flock are taken one after another; but if the Centinel be awake at the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the creeping Fowlers, and hear a Noiſe, it cries ſoftly, <hi>Grog, Grog,</hi> at which the Flock move not; but if this Centinel ſee or hear the Fowler approaching, he cries quickly, <hi>Bir, Bir,</hi> which would ſeem to import danger, ſince immediately after, all the Tribe take Wing, leaving the Fowler empty on the Rock, to return home <hi>re in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectâ,</hi> all his Labour for that Night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpent in vain. Here is a large Field of Diverſion for <hi>Apollonius Tyanae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> who is ſaid to have Travelled many Kingdoms over, to Learn
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:199743:38"/>the Language of Beaſts and Birds.</p>
               <p>Beſides this way of ſtealing upon them in the Night-time, they are alſo catched in common Gins of Horſe-Hair, from which they do ſtruggle leſs to extricate themſelves than any other Fowl, notwithſtanding their bigneſs and ſtrength; they are alſo caught in the Herring Loches with a Board ſet on purpoſe to float above Water, up-it a Herring is fixed, which the Gooſe perceiving, flies up to a competent height, until he finds himſelf making a ſtrait line above the Fiſh, and then bending his courſe perpendicularly piercing the Air, as an Arrow from a Bow, hits the Board, into which he runs his Bill with all his force irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verably, where he is unfortunately ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. The <hi>Solan</hi> Gooſe comes about the middle of <hi>March</hi> with a <hi>South Weſt</hi> Wind, warm Snow, or Rain, and goes away, according as the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:199743:38"/>determine the time, <hi>i. e.</hi> the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away, or leaving its Egg, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the Firſt, Second, or Third time he lays.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Fulmar,</hi> in Bigneſs equals the <hi>Malls</hi> of the Second rate; its Wings very long, the outſide of which are of a greyiſh white Colour, the Inſide and Breaſt all White, a thick Bill Two Inches long, Crooked and Prominent at the end, with wide Noſtrils in the middle of the Bill, all of a pale Colour; the upper Mandible, or Jaw, hangs over the lower on both ſides and point, his Feet pale, not very broad, with ſharp Toes, and a back Toe; he picks his Food out of the Back of live Whales, they ſay he uſes Sorrel with it, for both are found in his Neſt; he lays his Egg ordinarily the Firſt, Second, or Third Day of <hi>May;</hi> which is larger than that of a <hi>Solan</hi> Gooſe Egg, of a White Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and very Thin, the ſhell ſo very
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:199743:39"/>tender that it breaks in pieces if the Seaſon proves Rainy; when his Egg is once taken away, he lays no more for that Year, as other Fowls do, both a Second and Third time; the Young Fowl is brought forth in the middle of <hi>June,</hi> and is ready to take Wing before the Twentieth of <hi>July;</hi> he comes in <hi>November,</hi> the ſure Meſſenger of Evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidings, being always accompanied with boiſterous <hi>Weſt</hi> Winds, great Snow, Rain, or Hail, and is the only Sea-Fowl that ſtays here all the Year round, except the Month of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> and part of <hi>October.</hi> The Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants prefer this, whether Young or Old, to all other; the Old is of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate Taſte, being a mixture of Fat and Lean; the Fleſh White, no Blood is to be found but only in his Head and Neck; the Young is all Fat, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting the Bones, having no Blood but what is in his Head; and when
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:199743:39"/>the Young <hi>Fulmar</hi> is ready to take Wing, he being approached, ejects a quantity of pure Oyl out at his Bill, and will make ſure to hit any that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacks him, in the Face, though Seven Paces diſtant; this, they ſay, he uſes for his defence; but the Inhabitants take care to prevent this, by ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing the Fowl behind, having for this purpoſe a Wooden Diſh fixed to the end of their Rods, which they hold before his Bill as he ſpouts out the Oyl; they ſurprize him alſo from behind, by taking hold of his Bill, which they tie with a Thread, and upon their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn home they untie it with a Diſh under to receive the Oil; this Oil is ſometimes of a Reddiſh, ſometimes of a Yellow Colour, and the Inhabitants and other Iſlanders put a great value upon it, and uſe it as a <hi>Catholicon</hi> for Diſeaſes, eſpecially for any Aking in the Bones, Stitches, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſome in the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:199743:40"/>adjacent Iſles uſe it as a Purge, others as a Vomiter; it is hot in quality, and forces its paſſage through any Wooden Veſſel.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Fulmar</hi> is a ſure Prognoſticator of the <hi>Weſt</hi> Wind; if he comes to Land, there is no <hi>Weſt</hi> Wind to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected for ſome time, but if he keeps at Sea, or goes to Sea from the Land, whether the Wind blow from the <hi>South, North,</hi> or <hi>Eaſt,</hi> or whether it is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Calm, his keeping the Sea is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways a certain preſage of an approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Weſt</hi> Wind; from this Quarter he is obſerved to return with his Prey; his Egg is large as that of a <hi>Solan</hi> Gooſe, White in Colour, ſharp at one end, ſomewhat blunt at the other.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Scraber,</hi> ſo called in St. <hi>Kilda;</hi> in the <hi>Farn</hi> Iſlands, <hi>Puffinet;</hi> in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the <hi>Greenland Dove;</hi> its Bill ſmall, ſharp pointed, a little crooked at the end, and Prominent; it is as large as a
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:199743:40"/>Pigeon, its whole Body being Black, except a White ſpot on each Wing; his Egg Grey, ſharp at one end, blunt at the other.</p>
               <p>It comes in the Month of <hi>March,</hi> and in the Night-time, without regard to any Winds; it's always inviſible, except in the Night, being all Day ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther abroad at Fiſhing, or all the Day under ground upon its Neſt, which it digs very far under ground, from whence it never comes in Day-light; it picks its Food out of the live Whale, with which, they ſay, it uſes Sorrel, and both are found in its Neſt. The Young <hi>Puffin</hi> is Fat as the Young <hi>Fulmar,</hi> and goes away in <hi>Auguſt</hi> if its Firſt Egg be ſpar'd.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Lavy,</hi> ſo call'd by the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of St. <hi>Kilda;</hi> by the <hi>Welch,</hi> a <hi>Guillem;</hi> it comes near to the bigneſs of a Duck; its Head, upper-ſide of the Neck all downwards of a dark
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:199743:41"/>Brown, and White Breaſt, the Bill ſtrait and ſharp pointed; the upper Chop hangs over the lower; its Feet and Claws are Black.</p>
               <p>Its Egg in bigneſs is near to that of a Gooſe Egg, ſharp at one end, and blunt at the other; the Colour of it is pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily mix'd with Green and Black; others of them are of a pale Colour, with Red and Brown Streaks; but this laſt is very rare; this Egg for ordinary Food is by the Inhabitants, and others, preferred above all the Eggs had here: This Fowl comes with a <hi>South-Weſt</hi> Wind, if Fair, the Twentieth of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary;</hi> the time of its going away depends upon the Inhabitants taking or leaving its Firſt, Second, or Third Egg: If it ſtays upon Land for the ſpace of Three Days without intermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, it is a ſign of <hi>Southerly</hi> Wind and Fair Weather; but if it goes to Sea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:199743:41"/>the Third expire, it is then a ſign of a Storm.</p>
               <p>The Bird, by the Inhabitants called the <hi>Falk,</hi> the <hi>Raſor-Bill</hi> in the <hi>Weſt</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>Awk</hi> in the <hi>North,</hi> the <hi>Murre</hi> in <hi>Cornwall; Alca Hoeri.</hi> It is a ſize leſs than the <hi>Lavy;</hi> its Head, Neck, Back, and Tail, are Black; the inſide to the middle of the Throat, White; the Throat under the Chin of a dusky Black; beyond the Noſtrils in the upper Mandible, or Jaw, there is a furrow deeper than that in the <hi>Coulter Neb,</hi> the upper Chop crooked at the end, and hangs over the lower, both having tranſverſe furrows. It lays its Egg in <hi>May,</hi> its Young take Wing the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of <hi>July,</hi> if the Inhabitants do not determine its ſtay longer, by taking the Egg; which in bigneſs is next to the <hi>Lavy,</hi> or <hi>Guillem</hi> Egg, and is vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly Spotted, ſharp at one end, and blunt at the other.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:199743:42"/>
               <p>The <hi>Bouger,</hi> by thoſe in St. <hi>Kilda</hi> ſo called; <hi>Coulter-Neb</hi> by thoſe in the <hi>Farn</hi> Iſlands; and in <hi>Cornwal, Pope;</hi> it is of the ſize of a Pidgeon, its Bill is ſhort, broad, and compreſſed ſide-wiſe, contrary to the Bills of Ducks, of a Triangular Figure, and ending in a ſharp point, the upper Mandible, or Jaw, Arcuate and Crooked at the point; the Noſtrils are long Holes produced by the Aperture of the Mouth; the Bill is of two Colours; near the Head, of an Aſh Colour, and Red towards the point; the Feet are Yellow, the Claws of a dark Blue; all the Back Black, Breaſt and Belly White. They Breed in Holes under ground, and come with a <hi>South-Weſt</hi> Wind about the Twenty ſecond of <hi>March,</hi> lay their Egg the Twenty ſecond of <hi>April,</hi> and produce the Fowl the Twenty ſecond of <hi>May,</hi> if their Firſt Egg be not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:199743:42"/>away; it is ſharp at one end, and blunt on the other.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Aſſilag</hi> is as large as a <hi>Lint-White;</hi> Black Bill, wide Noſtrils at the upper part, Crooked at the point like the <hi>Fulmar</hi>'s Bill: It comes about the Twenty ſecond of <hi>March,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any regard to Winds, lays its Egg about the Twentieth of <hi>May,</hi> and produces the Fowl towards the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of <hi>October,</hi> then goes away about the end of <hi>November.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are Three ſorts of <hi>Sea-Malls</hi> here, the Firſt of a Grey Colour, in proportion near to a Gooſe: The Second ſort of <hi>Malls</hi> are conſiderably leſs, and of a Grey Colour; and the Third ſort is a White <hi>Mall,</hi> leſs than a Tame Duck; the Inhabitants call it <hi>Reddag;</hi> it comes the Fifteenth of <hi>April</hi> with a <hi>South-Weſt</hi> Wind, lays its Egg about the middle of <hi>May,</hi> and goes away in the Month of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:199743:43"/>
               <p>The <hi>Tirma,</hi> or <hi>Sea-Pie,</hi> by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants call'd <hi>Trilichan,</hi> comes in <hi>May,</hi> goes away in <hi>Auguſt;</hi> if it comes the beginning of <hi>May,</hi> it is a ſign of a good Summer; if later, the contrary is obſerved. This Fowl is Cloven-Footed, and conſequently Swims not.</p>
               <p>It is obſerved of all the Sea-Fowls here, that they are Fatter in time of Hatching than at other times, the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi> Geeſe excepted.</p>
               <p>Every Fowl lays an Egg Three dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent times (except the <hi>Gair-fowl</hi> and <hi>Fulmar,</hi> which lay but once); if the Firſt or Second Egg be taken away, every Fowl lays but one other Egg that Year, except the <hi>Sea-Malls,</hi> and they ordinarily lay the Third Egg, whether the Firſt and Second Eggs be taken away, or no.</p>
               <p>The Inhabirants obſerve, That when the <hi>April</hi> Moon goes far in <hi>May,</hi> the Fowls are Ten or Twelve Days later
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:199743:43"/>in laying their Eggs, than ordinarily they uſe to be.</p>
               <p>The Inhabitants likewiſe ſay, That of theſe Fowls, there firſt come over ſome Spies, or Harbingers, eſpecially of the <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe, tow'ring about the Iſlands where their Neſts are, and that when they have made a Review thereof they Fly away, and in Two or Three Days after, the whole Tribe are ſeen coming. Whither the Fowls Fly, and where they ſpend their Winter, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants are utterly ignorant of.</p>
               <p>The Eggs are found to be of an Aſtringent and Windy Quality to Strangers, but, it ſeems, are not ſo to the Inhabitants, who are uſed to Eat them from the Neſt. Our Men upon their arrival Eating greedily of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Coſtive and Feveriſh, ſome had the <hi>Hemorrhoid</hi> Veins ſwell'd; Mr. <hi>Camp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell</hi> and I were at no ſmall trouble be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we could reduce them to their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:199743:44"/>Temper; we ordered a Gliſter for them made of the Roots of <hi>Sedges,</hi> Freſh Butter, and Salt, which, being adminiſtred, had its wiſh'd-for effect; the Inhabitants reckoned this an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary performance, being, it ſeems, the firſt of this kind they ever had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to hear of.</p>
               <p>They preſerve their Eggs common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their Stone-Pyramids, ſcattering the burnt Aſhes of Turf under and about them, to defend them from the Air, drineſs being their only Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and moiſture their Corruption; they preſerve them Six, Seven, or Eight Months, as aboveſaid; and then they become Appetizing and Looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, eſpecially thoſe that begin to turn.</p>
               <p>That ſuch a great Number of Wild Fowls are ſo Tame, as to be eaſily ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the Rods and Gins, is not to be much admired by any who will be
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:199743:44"/>at the pains to conſider the reaſon, which is the great Inclination of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagating their Species; ſo powerful is that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or Natural Affection for their Off-ſpring, that they chuſe rather to die upon the Egg, or Fowl, than eſcape with their own Lives, (which they could do in a Minute) and leave ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe to be deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>It deſerves our conſideration to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect ſeriouſly upon the natural Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſity and Sagacity of theſe Animals in their Kind; which if compared with many Rational Creatures, do far out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrip them, and juſtly obey the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript of their Natures, by living up unto that Inſtinct that Providence has given them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:199743:45"/>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:199743:45"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Inhabitants. Their Pedegree: Complection: Strength: Diſeaſes: Cures: Plants: Religion: Notion of Spirits. Feſtivals: Anniverſary Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cade: Chappels: Crucifix: Lots: Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage: Baptiſm. Proprietor: Omer: Cubit. Envoy, his Salary, Entry. Steward's Retinue: His Reſidence: How far Limited. Tributary Cake. Mutton furniſhed by the Officer to the Steward every Sunday. Number of the Inhabitants: Their Kiln by turns. The Officer: His Precedence: Notion of Honour: The danger attending this Notion. Dexterity in Climbing. Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. Habit. Burials. Ale, how Brewed. Fowls preſerved. A Calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:199743:46"/>of the <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe conſumed by the Inhabitants laſt Year. Five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Stone-Pyramids for ſeveral uſes. The Inhabitant's Food. Great lovers of Tobacco. Their Boat, how nicely divided. Fire-Penny: Pot-Penny. No Money uſed here. The Rock-Fowl: How preſented by a Lover to his Miſtreſs. The <hi>Miſtreſs-Stone.</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of all Foreign Objects. Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE Inhabitants of this Iſle are Originally Deſcended of thoſe of the adjacent Iſles, <hi>Lewis, Harries, South</hi> and <hi>North Viſt, Skiy:</hi> Both Sexes are naturally very Grave, of a Fair Complection; ſuch as are not Fair are Natives only for an Age or two; but their Off-ſpring proves fairer than themſelves.</p>
               <p>There are Several of them would be reckoned among Beauties of the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:199743:46"/>firſt Rank, were they upon a level with others in their Dreſs.</p>
               <p>Both Men and Women are well Proportioned, nothing differing from thoſe of the Iſles and Continent. The preſent Generation comes ſhort of the laſt in Strength and Longevity. They ſhew'd us huge big Stones carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Fathers of ſome of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants now living; any of which is a Burthen too heavy for any two of the preſent Inhabitants to raiſe from the ground; and this change is all within the compaſs of Forty Years. But notwithſtanding this, any one In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> is always reputed ſtronger than two of the Inhabitants belonging to the Iſle of <hi>Harries,</hi> or the adjacent Iſles. Thoſe of St. <hi>Kilda</hi> have generally but very Thin Beards, and thoſe too do not appear till they arrive at the Age of Thirty, and in ſome not till after Thirty five; they have
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:199743:47"/>all but a few Hairs upon the upper Lip, and point of the Chin.</p>
               <p>Both Sexes have a Liſp, but more eſpecially the Women, neither of the two pronouncing the Letters, <hi>d, g,</hi> or <hi>r.</hi> I remember a Story of a <hi>Craker</hi> that Liſped (Two Years ago), the Boys of the place took notice of, and were pleaſed to hear him, and to Ape his Cry; one of the Steward's Men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding them, enquired the meaning of their Noiſe, which he told them was Ridiculous; they return'd anſwer, That it was worth his while to behold the ſport of a Liſping <hi>Craker,</hi> whom they Aped; but the Man replied, That they played the Fool, for the <hi>Craker</hi> diverted himſelf in Liſping af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them, and charged them with that Imperfection; the Boys no ſooner heard this, but away they ran, and left the <hi>Craker</hi> to Cry and Liſp as he pleaſed.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:199743:47"/>
               <p>There are ſome of both Sexes who have a Genius for <hi>Poetry,</hi> and are great admirers of Muſick: The Trump or <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Harp is all the Muſical Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they have, which diſpoſes them to Dance mightily. Their Sight is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary good, and they can diſcern things at a great diſtance: They have very good Memories, and are reſolute in their Undertakings, Chaſte and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and the Men reputed Jealous of their Wives. They Argue cloſely, and with leſs Paſſion than other Iſland<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or thoſe Inhabiting the High-lands on the Continent.</p>
               <p>They are reputed very Cunning, and there is ſcarce any Circumventing of them in Traffick and Bartering; the Voice of one is the Voice of all the reſt, they being all of a piece, their common Intereſt uniting them firmly together. They Marry very Young, the Women at about Thirteen
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:199743:48"/>or Fourteen Years of Age; and are nice in examining the Degrees of Conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinity before they Marry. They give Suck to their Children for the ſpace of Two Years. The moſt Ancient Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon among them at preſent, is not above Eighty Years of Age.</p>
               <p>Providence is very favourable to them in this, that they are not infeſted with ſeveral diſeaſes which are ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant in the other Parts of the World; the Diſtemper that moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails here, is a Spotted Fever, and that too confin'd to one Tribe, to whom this Diſeaſe is, as it were, become He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary; Others are liable to Fluxes, Fevers, Stitches, the Spleen; for all which they have but very few Remedies; to get away their Stitches, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly lie upon a warm Hearth, with the ſide affected downwards; this they look upon to be almoſt infallible for diſpelling the Humor, or Wind, that
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:199743:48"/>Torments them. The Small-Pox hath not been heard of in this Place for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Ages, except in one Inſtance, of Two of the Steward's Retinue, who not having been well recovered of it, upon their Arrival here, infected One Man only.</p>
               <p>The Plants produced here, are <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathum Vulgare,</hi> the Common Dock, Scurvy-Graſs round, being large as the Palm of the Hand, <hi>Mille-Foil, Burſa Paſtoris,</hi> Silver-Weed, or Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentine, Plantine, Sage, Chicken-Weed, Sorrel, long, or the common Sorrel; All-Hail, or <hi>Siderites,</hi> the <hi>Sea-Pinck, Tormentil,</hi> the <hi>Scurf upon the Stones,</hi> which has a Drying and Healing qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and is likewiſe uſed for Dying. The Inhabitants are ignorant of the Virtues of theſe Herbs; they never had a Potion of Phyſick given them in their Lives, nor know any thing of Phlebotomy; a Phiſician could not
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:199743:49"/>expect his Bread in this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
               <p>They have generally good Voices, and ſound Lungs; to this the <hi>Solan</hi> Gooſe Egg Supp'd Raw doth not a little contribute; they are ſeldom troubled with a Cough, except at the Steward's Landing; which is no leſs rare, than firmly believed by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the adjacent Iſles.</p>
               <p>Thoſe of St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> upon the whole, gave me this following account, That they always contract a Cough upon the Steward's Landing, and it proves a great deal more troubleſome to them in the Night-time, they then diſtilling a great deal of Flegm; this Indiſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on continues for ſome Ten, Twelve, or Fourteen Days; the moſt Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Remedy againſt this Diſeaſe, is their great and beloved <hi>Catholicon,</hi> the <hi>Giben, i. e.</hi> the Fat of their Fowls, with which they ſtuff the Stomach of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:199743:49"/>the <hi>Solan</hi> Gooſe, in faſhion of a Pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; this they put in the Infuſion of Oatmeal, which in their Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage they call <hi>Brochan;</hi> but it is not ſo effectual now as at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, becauſe of the frequent uſe of it. I told them plainly, That I thought all this Notion of Infection was but a meer fancy, and that, at leaſt, it could not always hold; at which they ſeemed offended, ſaying, That never any, before the Miniſter and my ſelf, was heard doubt of the truth of it; which is plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated upon the Landing of every Boat; adding further, That every De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign was always for ſome End, but here there was no room for any, where nothing could be propoſed; but for Confirmation of the whole, they appealed to the caſe of Infants at the Breaſt, who were likewiſe very ſubject to this Cough, but could not be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:199743:50"/>of affecting it, and therefore, in their Opinion, they were infected by ſuch as Lodged in their Houſes. There were ſcarce Young or Old in the Iſle whom I did not Examine par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly upon this Head, and all agreed in the Confirmation of it. They add farther, That when any Foreign Goods are brought thither, then the Cough is of longer Duration than otherwiſe. They remark, That if the Fever has been among thoſe of the Steward's Retinue, though before their Arrival there, ſome of the Inhabitants are Infected with it. If any of the Inhabitants of St. <hi>Kilda</hi> chance to live, though but a ſhort ſpace, in the Iſles of <hi>Harries, Skey,</hi> or any of the adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Iſles, they become Meagre, and contract ſuch a Cough, that the <hi>Giben</hi> muſt be had, or elſe they muſt return to their Native Soil. This <hi>Giben</hi> is more Sovereign for removing of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:199743:50"/>Coughs, being uſed by any other Iſlanders, than thoſe of, St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they love to have it frequently in their Meat as well as Drink, by which too frequent uſe of it, it loſes its virtue; it was remarkable, that after this infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Cough was over, we Strangers, and the Inhabitants of St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up the Number of about Two hundred and fifty; though we had fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently aſſembled upon the occaſion of Divine Service, yet neither Young nor Old among us all did ſo much as once Cough more.</p>
               <p>Some Thirteen Years ago the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſy broke out among them, and ſome of their Number Died by it; there are Two Families at preſent la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring under this Diſeaſe. The Symptoms of it are, their Feet begin to fail, their Appetite declines, their Faces become too Red, and break out in Pimples, they get a Hoarſeneſs,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:199743:51"/>and their Hair falls off from their Heads, the Crown of it Exulcerates and Bliſters, and laſtly, their Beards grow thinner than ordinary.</p>
               <p>This Diſeaſe may in a large mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure be aſcribed to their groſs Feeding, and that on thoſe Fat Fowls, as the <hi>Fulmar</hi> and the <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe; the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of which they keep for the ſpace of a whole Year, without Salt or Pepper to preſerve them; theſe they Eat Roaſted or Boiled.</p>
               <p>One of theſe Lepers, being with me one day at the <hi>Fulmar</hi>-Rock, impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuned me to give him a remedy for his Diſeaſe; I began to chide him for his ill Diet in Feeding ſo groſly; but find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the poor Fellow ready and impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citly diſpoſed to do whatever I ſhould enjoin, I bid him take example from the <hi>Fulmar,</hi> who, they ſay, Feeds ſometimes on <hi>Sorrel;</hi> this was a very ſurprizing Advice to him, but when
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:199743:51"/>he conſidered that the <hi>Fulmar</hi> required <hi>Sorrel</hi> to qualify the <hi>Whale,</hi> he was the ſooner perſuaded that his <hi>Giben</hi> and <hi>Gooſe</hi> might require the ſame; I advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him further, to abſtain from the <hi>Giben</hi> and <hi>Fat Fowls,</hi> which was no ſmall trouble to him, for he loved them exceedingly; I obliged him like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to mount the Hill <hi>Conager,</hi> a Mile in Height, once every Morning and Evening, and he was very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to comply with thoſe Injunctions for the ſpace of Three Days; in which ſhort time he made ſome advances towards recovering his almoſt loſt Speech and Appetite, for his Throat was well nigh quite ſtopp'd up; he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued this practice a Week longer, by which means he mended very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderably; and I left him fully reſolved to proceed in this practice, until he was perfectly reſtored to his former ſtate of Health. I had the occaſion
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:199743:52"/>to obſerve another of theſe Lepers rave for ſome Minutes, and when he was recovered to his Right Mind, he wrought at his ordinary Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>The Inhabitants are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> much of the Primitive Temper, neither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to Enthuſiaſm nor to Popery. They Swear not the Common Oaths that prevail in the World; when they refuſe or deny to give what is asked of them, they do it with a ſtrong Aſſeveration, which they expreſs em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatically enough in their Language to this purpoſe. <hi>You are no more to have it, than that if God had forbid it;</hi> and thus they expreſs the higheſt degree of paſſion. They do not ſo much as name the Devil once in their life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times.</p>
               <p>They leave off Working after Twelve of the Clock on <hi>Saturday,</hi> as being an ancient. Cuſtom delivered
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:199743:52"/>down to them from their Anceſtors, and go no more to it till <hi>Monday</hi> Morning. They believe in <hi>God the Father, the Son, and Holy Ghoſt;</hi> and a State of Future Happineſs and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and that all Events, whether Good or Bad, are determined by <hi>God.</hi> They uſe a ſet Form of Prayer at the Hoiſing of their Sails: They lie down, riſe, and begin their Labours in the Name of God. They have a Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that Spirits are embodied; theſe they fancy to be locally in Rocks, Hills, and where-ever they liſt in an inſtant.</p>
               <p>There are Three Chappels in this Iſle, each of them with one end towards the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> the other towards the <hi>Weſt;</hi> the Altar always placed at the <hi>Eaſt</hi> End; the firſt of theſe is called <hi>Chriſt Chappel,</hi> near the Village; it is covered and thatched after the ſame manner with their Houſes; there is a Brazen
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:199743:53"/>
                  <hi>Cruciſix</hi> lies upon the Altar, not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding a Foot in length, the Body is compleatly done, diſtended, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Crown on, all in the Crucified Poſture; they have it in great Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, though they pay no kind of Adoration or Worſhip to it, nor do they either handle or ſee it, except up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Occaſions of Marriage, and Swearing deciſive Oaths, which puts an end to all Strife, and both theſe Ceremonies are Publickly performed. The Church-yard is about an Hundred Paces in Circumference, and is fenced in with a little Stone Wall, within which they Bury their Dead; they take care to keep the Church-yard perfectly Clean, void of any kind of Naſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and their Cattel have no acceſs to it. The Inhabitants, Young and Old, come to the Church-yard every <hi>Sunday</hi> Morning, the Chappel not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Capacious enough to receive them;
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:199743:53"/>here they devoutly ſay the Lord's Prayer, Creed, and Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>They obſerve the Feſtivals of <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, Eaſter, Good-Friday,</hi> St. <hi>Columba</hi>'s Day, and that of <hi>All Saints;</hi> upon this they have an Anniverſary Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cade, the Number of their Horſes not exceeding Eighteen; theſe they Mount by turns, having neither Saddle nor Bridle of any kind, except a Rope, which Manages the Horſe only on one ſide; they Ride from the Shoar to the Houſe, and then after each Man has performed his Tour, the Show is at an end. They are very Charitable to their Poor, of whom there are not at preſent above Three, and theſe care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully provided for, by this little Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, each particular Family contributing according to their Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity for their Neceſſities; their Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is enquired into Weekly, or
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:199743:54"/>Monthly, as their Occaſions ſerve; but more eſpecially at the time of their Feſtivals, they ſlay ſome Sheep on purpoſe to be diſtributed among the Poor, with Bread proportionable; they are Charitable to Strangers in Diſtreſs, this they had opportunity to expreſs to a Company or <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniards</hi> who loſt their Ship at <hi>Rokol</hi> in the Year 1686, and came in, in a Pinnace to St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> where they were plentifully, ſupplied with Barly-Bread, Butter, Cheeſe, <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe, Eggs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> both Seamen and Inhabitants were <hi>Barbarians</hi> one to another, the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants ſpeaking only the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Tongue, to which the <hi>French</hi> and the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were altogether Strangers; upon their Landing they pointed to the <hi>Weſt,</hi> Naming <hi>Rokol</hi> to the Inhabitants, and after that, they pointed downward with their Finger, ſignifying the Slink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Periſhing of their Veſſel;
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:199743:54"/>they ſhewed them <hi>Rokol</hi> in the Sea Map, far <hi>Weſt</hi> off St. <hi>Kilda.</hi> This, and much more, the Maſters of theſe Ships told to a Prieſt in the next Iſland who underſtood <hi>French.</hi> The Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants acquainted me that the Pinnace which carried the Seamen from <hi>Rokol</hi> was ſo very low, that the Crew ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a Foot height of Canvaſs round it all, and began to Work at it upon <hi>Sunday,</hi> at which the Inhabitants were aſtoniſhed, and being highly diſſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, plucked the Hatchets and other Inſtruments out of their Hands, and did not reſtore them till <hi>Monday</hi> Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>The Inhabitants had occaſion to ſhew great kindneſs to a Boat's Crew that was driven from the oppoſite Iſle <hi>South Wiſt,</hi> whither they themſelves were driven afterwards, and where they were treated with no leſs Civility and Kindneſs than the abovementioned
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:199743:55"/>had been by them: So that it may be ſaid of them with great Juſtice, That their Charity is as Extenſive as the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of it.</p>
               <p>The Second of theſe Chappels bears the Name of St. <hi>Columba,</hi> the Third of St. <hi>Brianan;</hi> both Built after the manner of <hi>Chriſt's Chappel;</hi> having Church-yards belonging to them, and they are a Quarter of a Mile diſtance betwixt each Chappel.</p>
               <p>They told me of a Ship that dropp'd Anchor in the Mouth of the Bay the preceeding Year, and that the Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers aboard her were not Chriſtians; I enquired if their Interpreter, who they ſaid ſpoke bad <hi>Iriſh,</hi> had owned this to be a Truth, they anſwered, <hi>not;</hi> but that they knew this by their Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and that in theſe Three particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars; the Firſt was the Working upon <hi>Sunday,</hi> carrying ſeveral Boats full of Stones aboard for Ballaſt; the Second
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:199743:55"/>was the taking away ſome of their Cows without any return for them, except a few <hi>Iriſh</hi> Copper Pieces; and the Third was, the Attempt made by them to Raviſh their Women, a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice altogether unknown in St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> where there has not been one inſtance of Fornication or Adultery for many Ages before this time; I remember they told me, that the Bribe offered for Debauching the poor Women, was a piece of Broad Money, than which there could be nothing leſs Charming in a place where the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants cannot diſtinguiſh a Guinea from a Sixpence.</p>
               <p>Their Marriages are Celebrated af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the following Manner; when any Two of them have agreed to take one another for Man and Wife, the Officer who preſides over them, ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons all the Inhabitants of both Sexes to <hi>Chriſt's Chappel,</hi> where being aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:199743:56"/>he enquires publickly if there be any lawful Impediment why theſe Parties ſhould not be joined in the Bond of Matrimony? And if there be no Objection to the contrary, he then enquires of the Parties if they are reſolved to live together in Weal and Woe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> After their Aſſent, he declares them Married Perſons, and then deſires them to Ratify this their Solemn Promiſe in the preſence of God and the People, in order to which the Crucifix is tender'd to them, and both put their Right Hands upon it, as the Ceremony by which they Swear Fidelity one to another during their life-time.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Campbel,</hi> the Miniſter, Married in this manner Fifteen Pair of the Inhabitants on the Seventeenth of <hi>June,</hi> who immediately after their Marriage, join'd in a Country Dance, having only a Bagpipe for their Muſick, which pleaſed them exceedingly.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:199743:56"/>
               <p>They Baptize in the following man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; the Parent calls in the Officer, or any of his Neighbours to Baptize his Child, and another to be Sponſor; he that performs the Miniſter's Part being told what the Child's Name is to be, ſays, <hi>A. B. I Baptize thee to your Father and your Mother, in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt;</hi> then the Sponſor takes the Child in his Arms, as doth his Wife as Godmother, and ever after this there is a Friendſhip be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Parent and the Sponſor, which is eſteemed ſo ſacred and inviola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that no Accident, how croſs ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, is able to ſet them at variance; and it reconciles ſuch as have been at Enmity formerly.</p>
               <p>This Iſle belongs in Property to the Laird of <hi>Mack-Leod,</hi> Head of one of the Ancienteſt Families of <hi>Scotland;</hi> it is never Farmed, but moſt commonly beſtowed upon ſome Favourite, one
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:199743:57"/>of his Friends or Followers, who is called <hi>Steward of the Iſte.</hi> The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Steward's Name is <hi>Alexander Mack-Leod,</hi> who pays Yearly to his Maſter an Acknowledgment of the various Products of this Iſle. This Steward viſits St. <hi>Kilda</hi> every Summer, and upon his Arrival he and his Reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue have all the Milk in the Iſle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on them in a Treat; there is another beſtowed on them upon St. <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumba</hi>'s Day, the Fifteenth of <hi>Junes;</hi> we had a ſhare of this Second Treat. The Steward's Retinue conſiſt of Forty, Fifty, or Sixty Perſons, and among them, perhaps, the moſt Meagre in the Pariſh are carried thither to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruited with good Chear; but this Retinue is now retrenched, as alſo ſome of their Ancient and unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Exactions.</p>
               <p>The Steward lives upon the Charge of the Inhabitants until the time that
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:199743:57"/>the <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe are ready to Fly, which the Inhabitants think long enough; the Daily Allowance paid by them is very regularly exacted, with regard to their reſpective Proportions of Lands and Rocks; there is not a parcel of Men in the World more ſcrupulouſly nice and punctilious in maintaining their Liberties and Properties than theſe are, being moſt Religiouſly fond of their Ancient Laws and Statutes; nor will they by any means conſent to Alter their firſt (though unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able) Conſtitutions; and we had a pregnant Inſtance of this their Genius for preſerving their Ancient Cuſtoms; they have unchangeably continued their firſt and Ancient Meaſures, as the <hi>Maile, Amir,</hi> and <hi>Cubit;</hi> this <hi>Maile</hi> contains Ten Pecks: The <hi>Amir</hi> which they at preſent make uſe of, is proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly the <hi>Hebrew Omer,</hi> which contains near Two Pecks; the <hi>Cubit,</hi> or in
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:199743:58"/>their Language, <hi>Lave Keile, i. e.</hi> an Hand of Wood, is the diſtance from the Elbow to the Finger's ends; this they only uſe in Meaſuring their Boats: The <hi>Amir,</hi> or rather <hi>Half Amir,</hi> as they call it, is compoſed of thin Boards, and as they confeſs his been uſed theſe Fourſcore Years; in which tract of time it is conſiderably fallen ſhort of the meaſure of which it was at firſt, which they themſelves do not altogether deny; the <hi>Steward</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſate this Loſs, pretends to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Cuſtom of adding the Hand of him that Meaſures the Corn to the <hi>Amir</hi> ſide, holding ſome of the Barly above the due Meaſure, which the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants complain of as unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; the <hi>Steward</hi> to ſatisfy them, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to Refer the Debate to Mr. <hi>Camp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi>'s Deciſion and mine, they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves being to propoſe their Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Two of his Retinue, who
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:199743:58"/>were well ſeen in the Cuſtoms of this place, in time of ſome of the former Stewards, being appointed to Anſwer them, and he promiſed that he would acquieſce in the Deciſion, though it ſhould prove to his Prejudice; but they would not alter that Meaſure if <hi>Mack-Leod</hi> did not expreſly, Command the ſame to be done, being perſuaded that he would not in the leaſt alter that Meaſure which his and their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors had had in ſuch Eſteem for ſo many Ages. So greats was their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for this <hi>Amir,</hi> that they unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly determined to ſend the Officer as Envoy (according to the Ancient Cuſtom) to repreſent their caſe to <hi>Mack-Leod;</hi> this was the reſult of a General Council, in which the Maſter of every Family has a Vote, ſince every Family pays this Officer an <hi>Amir</hi> of Barly <hi>per Annum,</hi> to maintain his Character.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:199743:59"/>
               <p>This Officer as ſuch, is obliged to adjuſt the reſpective Proportions of Lands, Graſs, and Rocks, and what elſe could be claimed by virtue of the laſt <hi>Tack,</hi> or Leaſe, which is never longer than for Three Years, conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended to by the Steward; nay, heis obliged always to diſpute with the Steward for what is due to any of them, and never to give over until he has obtained his Demand, or put the Steward into ſuch a Paſſion, that he gives the Officer at leaſt Three Strokes with his Cudgel over the Crown of his Head; after theſe Three Strokes he has done the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt that is required of him by their Ancient Cuſtoms. I enquired of the Officer (who told me this paſſage) what if the Steward give him but One Blow over the Crown, he anſwered, That the Inhabitants would not be ſatisfied if he did not ſo far plead as
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:199743:59"/>to Irritate the Steward to give both a Second and a Third Blow; I had the farther curioſity to enquire of the Steward himſelf if he was wont to Treat the Officer in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; who anſwered, That it was an Ancient Cuſtom, which in his ſhort time he had not had occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to practiſe, but if he ſhould, he would not confine himſelf to the Number of Three Blows, if the Officer ſhould prove Indiſcreet.</p>
               <p>The Steward beſtows ſome Acres of Land upon the Officer for ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him and the Inhabitants; he gives him likewiſe the Bonnet worn by himſelf upon his going out of the Iſland; the Steward's Wife leaves with the Officer's Wife the <hi>Kerch,</hi> or Head-dreſs worn by her ſelf, and ſhe beſtows likewiſe upon her an Ounce of <hi>Indigo.</hi> The Steward has a
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:199743:60"/>large Cake of Barly preſented to him by the Officer at every Meal, and it muſt be made ſo large as ſhall be ſufficient to ſatisfy Three Men at a time, and by way of Eminence it is baked in the Form of a Triangle, and furrowed Twice round; the Officer is likewiſe obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to furniſh the Steward with Mutton, or Beef, to his Dinner every <hi>Sunday</hi> during his Reſidence in the Iſland.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding theſe reciprocal acts of Kindneſs, this Officer muſt be allowed to go in quality of an Envoy to <hi>Mack-Leod</hi> againſt the Steward, upon extraordinary Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, if the Commonwealth have any Grievances to Redreſs, as that of the <hi>Amir</hi> now depending; but the Commiſſion given him is Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited, the whole Boat's Crew be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing joined in Commiſſion with him,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:199743:60"/>and are a Check upon him, leſt his Dependance upon the Steward might be apt to biaſs him; he makes his Entry very ſubmiſſively, taking off his Bonnet at a great diſtance when he appears in <hi>Mack-Leod</hi>'s pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, Bowing his Head and Hand low near to the Ground, his Reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue doing the like behind him one after another, making, as it were, a Chain; this being their manner of Walking both at Home and Abroad, for they Walk not a-breaſt as others do; and in making their Purchaſe among the Rocks, one leads the Van, and the reſt follow.</p>
               <p>The Number of People Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this Iſle at preſent, is about One hundred and eighty, who in the Steward's abſence are Governed by one <hi>Donald Mack-Gill-Colm,</hi> as their <hi>Meijre,</hi> which imports an <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer;</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:199743:61"/>this Officer was anciently Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, or at leaſt approved of by the People, before the Steward ſettled him in his Office, but now the Stewards have the Nomination of him abſolutely; he is Preſident over them in all their Debates, takes care that the Lots be managed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially, that none to whoſe ſhare they fall may have cauſe to repine, whether it be for the Steward's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, or that of the Commonwealths; the uſe of the Lots, together with the Crucifix, do mightily contribute to their Peace and Quiet, keeping every one within his proper Bounds. It muſt needs be a very odd caſe indeed that falls not within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pals of either of theſe Two to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine; when any caſe happens which does not fall under the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of Lots, and it is capable of being decided only by the Oath
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:199743:61"/>of the Parties, then the Crucifix muſt determine the matter; and if it ſhould prove to be a caſe of the higheſt Importance, any of them is at liberty to refer it to his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour's Oath, without any ſuſpition of Perjury, provided the Ceremony of touching the Crucifix with their Right Hand be obſerved; and this is always publickly performed.</p>
               <p>If any Man is guilty of Beating his Neighbour, he is liable to a Fine not exceeding the Value of Two Shillings <hi>Sterling;</hi> if any has Beat his Neighbour ſo as to draw Blood from him; he is liable to a Fine, but it muſt not exceed Four Shillings and Sixpence; theſe Crimes are complained of by the Officer to the Steward upon his Arrival, who either exacts the whole, or diſpences with the Fines, as he judges convenient for their future Quiet and Peace.</p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:199743:62"/>
               <p>They have only one common <hi>Kiln,</hi> which ſerves them all by turns, as the Lots fall to their ſhare; he whoſe Lot happens to be laſt does not reſent it at all.</p>
               <p>The Officer by virtue of his Place, is obliged through a point of Honour to be the Firſt that Lands in the Leſſer Iſles and Rocks, from whence they carry their Fowls and Eggs, and not without ſome trouble too. This Notion of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour expoſes him to frepuent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; and, perhaps, it may not be unpleaſant to deſcribe it as I have ſeen it practiſed; and 'tis thus; When they have come as near to the Rock as they think may conſiſt with the ſafety of the Boat, which is not a little toſſed by the raging of the Sea, thoſe, whoſe turn then it is, are employed with Poles to keep off the Boat, that is in great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:199743:62"/>in regard of the violence of the Waves beating upon the Rock, and they are to watch the Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of the Calmeſt Wave; upon the firſt appearance of which, the Officer jumps out upon the Rock; if there be any apparent Danger, he ties a Rope about his Middle, with one end of it faſtened to the Boat; if he has Landed ſafe, he then fixes his Feet in a ſecure place, and by the aſſiſtance of this Rope draws up all the Crew to him, except thoſe whoſe turn it is to look af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Boat; but if in jumping out he falls into the Sea, (as his fortune is ſo to do ſometimes) then he is drawn into the Boat again by that part of the Rope that is ſo faſtened to it, and the next then whoſe turn it is muſt try his fortune, the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer after his fall being ſuppoſed to be ſufficiently fatigu'd, ſo that he is
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:199743:63"/>not obliged to adventure his Perſon again to a Second Hazard upon this occaſion, eſpecially he being expoſed to the greateſt danger that offers upon their Landing when they return back again to the Iſle, where the Sea often rages, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obliged then by virtue of his Office to ſtay in the Boat, after the whole Crew are Landed, where he muſt continue employing his Pole, until the Boat be either brought ſafe to Land, or elſe ſplit upon the Rocks.</p>
               <p>They furniſh themſelves with Ropes to carry them through the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acceſſible Rocks; of theſe Ropes there are only Three in the whole Iſland, each of them Twenty four Fathoms in length; and they are either knit together and lengthned by tying the one to the other, or uſed ſeparately as occaſion requires;
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:199743:63"/>the chief thing upon which the Strength of theſe Ropes depends, is Cows Hides Salted, and cut out in one long piece, this they twiſt round the ordinary Rope of Hemp, which ſecures it from being cut by the Rocks; they join ſometimes at the lower end Two Ropes, one of which they tie about the middle of one Climber, and another about the middle of another, that theſe may aſſiſt one another in caſe of a fall; but the Misfortune is, that ſometimes the one happens to pull down the other, and ſo both fall into the Sea; but if they eſcape (as they do commonly of late) they get an incredible Number of Eggs and Fowls.</p>
               <p>The Ropes belong to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, and are not to be uſed without the general Conſent of all; the Lots determine the Time, Place,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:199743:64"/>and Perſons for uſing them, they get together in Three Days a much greater Number of Fowls and Eggs than their Boat is able to carry away, and therefore what is over and above they leave behind in their Stone-Pyramids: They catch their Fowls with Gins made of Horſe-Hair, theſe are tied to the end of their Fiſhing-Rods, with which the Fowlers creep through the Rocks indiſcernably, putting the Nooſe over their Heads about their Necks, and ſo draw them inſtantly; they uſe likewiſe Hair Gins which they ſet upon plain Rocks, both the ends faſtned by a Stone, and ſo catch Forty or Fifty a Day with them.</p>
               <p>The Inhabitants, I muſt tell you, run no ſmall danger in the queſt of the Fowls and Eggs, inſomuch that I fear it would be thought an
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:199743:64"/>
                  <hi>Hyperbole</hi> to relate the Inacceſſible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Steepneſs, and Height, of thoſe formidable Rocks which they ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to climb. I my ſelf have ſeen ſome of them Climb up the Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of a Rock with their Backs to it, making uſe only of their Heels and Elbows, without any other Aſſiſtance; and they have this way ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired a Dexterity in Climbing beyond any I ever yet ſaw; Neceſſity has made them apply themſelves to this, and Cuſtom has perfected them in it; ſo that it is become familiar to them almoſt from their Cradles, the young Boys of Three Years Old begin to Climb the Walls of their Houſes: Their frequent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſes of Climbing, together with the fatal End of ſeveral in the Exerciſe of it, is the ſame to them, as that of Fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Killing is with Soldiers, and ſo is become as familiar and leſs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:199743:65"/>to them, than otherwiſe cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it would be. I ſaw Two Young Men, to whoſe ſhare the Lots fell in <hi>June</hi> laſt, for taking the Neſt of a Hawk (which was in a High Rock above the Sea) bringing home the Hawks in a few Minutes, without any Aſſiſtance at all.</p>
               <p>Their Dogs are likewiſe very dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous in Climbing and bringing out from their Holes thoſe Fowls which build their Neſts far under-ground, ſuch as the <hi>Scraber, Puffinet,</hi> &amp;c. which they carry in their Teeth to their Maſters, letting them fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ground before them, though aſleep.</p>
               <p>The Inhabitants ſpeak the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Tongue only; they expreſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſlowly but pertinently, and have the ſame Language with thoſe
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:199743:65"/>of <hi>Harries</hi> and other Iſles, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in its Purity.</p>
               <p>Their Habit Antiently was of Sheepskins, which has been wore by ſeveral of the Inhabitants now living; the Men at this day wear a Short Doublet reaching to their Waſte, about that a double Plait of Plad, both ends join'd together with the Bone of a <hi>Fulmar;</hi> this Plad reaches no further than their Knees, and is above the Haunches girt about with a Belt of Leather; they wear ſhort Caps of the ſame Colour and Shape with the <hi>Capuchins,</hi> but ſhorter; and on <hi>Sundays</hi> they wear Bonnets; ſome of late have got Breeches, and they are Wide and Open at the Knees; they wear Cloth Stockins, and go without Shoes in the Summer-time; their Leather is dreſs'd with the Roots of <hi>Tormentil.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:199743:66"/>
               <p>The Women wear upon their Heads a Linnen Dreſs, ſtrait before, and drawing to a ſmall point behind below the Shoulders, a Foot and an half in length, and a Lock of about Sixty Hairs hanging down each Cheek, reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Breaſts, the lower end tied with a Knot; their Plad, which is the upper Garment, is faſtened upon their Breaſts with a large round Buckle of Braſs in form of a Circle; the Buckle antiently worn by the Steward's Wives were of Silver, but the preſent Steward's Wife makes no uſe of either this Dreſs or Buckle. The Women In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting this Iſle wear no Shoes nor Stockins in the Summer-time; the only and ordinary Shoes they wear, are made of the Necks of <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe, which they cut above the Eyes, the Crown of the Head ſerves for the Heel, the whole Skin being
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:199743:66"/>cut cloſe at the Breaſt, which end being ſowed, the Foot enters into it, as into a piece of narrow Stockin; this Shoe doth not Wear above Five Days, and if the Down ſide be next the Ground, then not above Three or Four Days; but, however, there is plenty of them, ſome Thouſands being Catch'd, or, as they term it, <hi>Stolen</hi> every <hi>March.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Both Sexes wear courſe <hi>Flannel</hi> Shirts, which they put off when they go to Bed; they thicken their Cloaths upon <hi>Flakes,</hi> or Mats of Hay twiſted and woven together in ſmall Ropes; they work hard at this Employment, firſt making uſe of their Hands, and at laſt of their Feet; and when they are at this work, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſing all the time, one of their Number acting the part of a Prime Chantreſs, whom all the reſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and Obey.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:199743:67"/>
               <p>They put the Faces of their Dead towards the Eaſt when they Bury them, and bewail the Death of their Relations exceſſively, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe Occaſions make doleful Songs; which they call <hi>Laments.</hi> Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the news of the late <hi>Mack-Leod</hi>'s Death, they abandoned their Houſes, Mourning Two Days in the Field; they Kill a Cow, or Sheep, before the Interment, but if it be in the Spring, this Ceremony then is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed, becauſe the Cattel are at that time Poor and Lean, but, however, they are to be Kill'd as ſoon as ever they become Fat.</p>
               <p>Their ordinary Food is Barly and ſome Oat-Bread Baked with Water; they Eat all the Fowls, already de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed, being dried in their Stone-Houſes, without any Salt or Spice to preſerve them; and All their Beef and Mutton is Eaten freſh, after the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:199743:67"/>ſame manner they uſe the <hi>Giben,</hi> or Fat of their Fowls; this <hi>Giben</hi> is by daily Experience found to be a Sovereign Remedy for the Healing of Green Wounds; it cured a <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi> in an Inhabitant of the Iſle of <hi>Lewis,</hi> and a <hi>Fiſtula</hi> in one <hi>Nichol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of <hi>Sky,</hi> in St. <hi>Maries</hi> Pariſh; this was performed by <hi>John Mack-Lean,</hi> Chirurgeon there: They Boil the Sea-Plants, <hi>Dulſe,</hi> and <hi>Slake,</hi> melting the <hi>Giben</hi> upon them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Butter, and upon the Roots of Silver-Weed and Dock Boiled, and alſo with their Scurvy-Graſs ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, which is very Purgative, and here it is of an extraordinary Breadth. They uſe this <hi>Giben</hi> with their Fiſh, and it is become the common Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hicle that conveys all their Food down their Throats. They are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done for want of Salt, of which as yet they are but little ſenſible; they
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:199743:68"/>uſe no ſet times for their Meals, but are determined purely by their Appetites.</p>
               <p>They uſe only the Aſhes of <hi>Sea-Ware</hi> for Salting their Cheeſe, and the ſhorteſt (which grows in the Rocks) is only uſed by them, that being reckoned the Mildeſt.</p>
               <p>Their Drink is Water, or Whey, commonly: They Brew Ale but rarely, uſing the Juice of <hi>Nettle-Roots,</hi> which they put in a Diſh with a little Barley-Meal Dough; theſe <hi>Sowens,</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> Flummery) being blended together, produce, good Yeſt, which puts their Wort into a Ferment, and makes good Ale, ſo that when they Drink plentifully of it, it diſpoſes them to Dance Merrily.</p>
               <p>They preſerve the <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe in their Pyramids for the ſpace of a Year, ſlitting them in the Back, for they have no Salt to keep them with.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:199743:68"/>They have Built above Five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Stone Pyramids for their Fowls, Eggs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We made particular Enquiry af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Number of <hi>Solan</hi> Geeſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed by each Family the Year before we came there, and it amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Twenty two thouſand ſix hundred in the whole Iſland, which they ſaid was leſs than they ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily did, a great many being loſt by the badneſs of the Seaſon, and the great Current into which they muſt be thrown when they take them, the Rock being of ſuch an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Height, that they cannot reach the Boat.</p>
               <p>There is one Boat Sixteen Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits long, which ſerves the whole Commonwealth; it is very curiouſly divided into Apartments proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their Lands and Rocks; every Individual has his ſpace di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:199743:69"/>to an Hair's breadth, which his Neighbour cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croach ſo much as to lay an Egg upon it.</p>
               <p>Every Partner in Summer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides a large Turf to cover his ſpace of the Boat, thereby defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it from the Violence of the Sun, which (in its Meridian Height) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flects moſt vehemently from the Sea, and Rock, upon which the Boat lies; at the drawing of it up, both Sexes are employed pulling a long Rope at the Fore-end; they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined in uniting their. Strength, by the Cryer, who is therefore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted from being obliged to draw the Boat.</p>
               <p>There is but one Steel and Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-Box in all this Commonwealth; the Owner whereof fails not upon every occaſion of ſtriking Fire in the leſſer Iſles, to go thither, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:199743:69"/>act Three Eggs, or one of the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Fowls from each Man as a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for his ſervice; this by them is called the <hi>Fire-Penny,</hi> and this Capitation is very uneaſy to them; I bid them try their Chryſtal with their Knives, which when they ſaw it did ſtrike Fire, they were not a little aſtoniſhed, admiring at the ſtrangeneſs of the thing, and at the ſame time accuſing their own Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, conſidering the quantity of Chryſtal growing under the Rock of their Coaſt. This Diſcovery has delivered them from the <hi>Fire-Penny</hi> Tax, and ſo they are no longer liable to it.</p>
               <p>They have likewiſe a <hi>Pot-Penny</hi> Tax, which is exacted in the ſame manner as the <hi>Fire-Penny</hi> was, but is much more reaſonable; for the Pot is carried to the Inferior Iſles for the publick uſe, and is in hazard
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:199743:70"/>of being broken; ſo that the Own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers may juſtly exact upon this ſcore, ſince any may venture his Pot when he pleaſes. When they have beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome Hours in Fowling about the Rocks, and caught a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Number, they ſit down near the face of it to refreſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and in the mean time they ſingle out the Fatteſt of their Fowls, plucking them bare, which they carry home to their Wives, or Miſtreſſes, as a great Preſent, and it is always accepted very kindly from them, and could not otherwiſe be, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great Ingratitude, ſeeing theſe Men ordinarily expoſe themſelves to very great danger, if not hazard their Lives, to procure thoſe Preſents for them.</p>
               <p>In the face of the Rock, <hi>South</hi> from the Town, is the famous Stone, known by the Name of the <hi>Miſtreſs-Stone;</hi>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:199743:70"/>it reſembles a Door exactly, and is in the very front of this Rock, which is Twenty or Thirty Fathom perpendicular in Height, the Figure of it being diſcernable about the diſtance of a Mile: Upon the Lintel of this Door, every Batchelor-Wooer is by an Antient Cuſtom obliged in honour to give a Specimen of his Affection for the Love of his Miſtreſs, and it is thus; He is to ſtand on his Left Foot, having the one half of his Sole over the Rock, and then he draws the Right Foot further out to the Left, and in this Poſture Bowing, he puts both his Fiſts further out to the Right Foot; and then after he has per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed this, he has acquired no ſmall Reputation, being always af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it accounted worthy of the fineſt Miſtreſs in the World: They firmly believe that this Atchievement is
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:199743:71"/>always attended with the deſired Succeſs.</p>
               <p>This being the Cuſtom of the Place, one of the Inhabitants very gravely deſired me to let him know the time limited by me for trying of this piece of Gallantry before I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to leave the place, that he might attend me; I told him this Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance would have a quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary effect upon me, by robbing me both of my Life and Miſtreſs at the ſame Moment; but he was of a contrary Opinion, and inſiſted on the good Fortune attending it; but I muſt confeſs all his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were too weak to make me attempt the Experiment.</p>
               <p>They take their meaſures in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the leſſer Iſlands from the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the Heavens; for when it is Clear or Cloudy in ſuch a Quarter, it is a Prognoſtick of Wind
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:199743:71"/>or Fair Weather; and when the Waves are high on the <hi>Eaſt</hi> point of the Bay, it is an infallible Sign of a Storm, eſpecially if they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear very White, even though the Weather be at that time Calm.</p>
               <p>If the Waves in the Bay make a noiſe as they break before they beat upon the Shoar, it is alſo an infallible forerunner of a <hi>Weſt</hi> Wind; if a Black Cloud appears above the <hi>South</hi> ſide of the Bay, a <hi>South</hi> Wind follows ſome Hours afterwards. It is obſerved of the Sea betwixt St. <hi>Kilda</hi> and the Iſles <hi>Lewis, Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> &amp;c. that it rages more with a <hi>North</hi> Wind, than when it Blows from any other Quarter. And it is likewiſe obſerved to be leſs raging with the <hi>South</hi> Wind than any other.</p>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:199743:72"/>
               <p>They know the time of the Day by the Motion of the Sun from one Hill or Rock to another; upon ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe the Sun is obſerved to appear at different times; and when the Sun doth not appear, they mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Day by the Ebbing and Flowing of the Sea, which they can tell exactly, though they ſhould not ſee the Shoar for ſome Days toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Their knowledge of the Tides depends upon the changes of the Moon, which they likewiſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, and are very nice in it.</p>
               <p>They uſe for their Diverſion ſhort Clubs and Balls of Wood; the Sand is a fair Field for this Sport and Exerciſe, in which they take great Pleaſure and are very nimble at it; they play for ſome Eggs, Fowls, Hooks, or Tobacco; and ſo eager are they for Victory, that they ſtrip
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:199743:72"/>themſelves to their Shirts to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it: They uſe Swimming and Diving, and are very expert in both.</p>
               <p>The Women have their Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies in the middle of the Village, where they diſcourſe of their Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, but in the mean time em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying their Diſtaff, and Spinning in order to make their Blankets; they Sing and Jeſt for Diverſion, and in their way, underſtand Poetry, and make Rhimes in their Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. Both Men and Women are very Courteous; as often as they paſſed by us every Day, they Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted us with their ordinary Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliment of <hi>God ſave you;</hi> each of them making their reſpective Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſies.</p>
               <p>Both Sexes have a great Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Novelty; and, perhaps, any thing may be thought new with
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:199743:73"/>them that is but different from their way of managing Land, Cattel, Fowls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A parcel of them were always attending the Miniſter and me, admiring our Habit, Behaviour; and, in a word, all that we did or ſaid was wonderful in their Eſteem; but above all, Writing was the moſt aſtoniſhing to them; they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conceive how it is poſſible for any Mortal to expreſs the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions of his Mind in ſuch Black Characters upon White Paper. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had with admiration ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued upon this Subject, I told them That within the compaſs of Two Years or leſs, if they pleaſed, they might eaſily be taught to Read and Write, but they were not of the Opinion that either of them could be obtained, at leaſt by them, in an Age.</p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:199743:73"/>
               <p>The Officer in his Embaſſy in <hi>July</hi> laſt, Travelled ſo far as to Land on the Continent next to <hi>Sky,</hi> and it was a long Journy for a Native of St. <hi>Kilda</hi> ſo to do, for ſcarce any of the Inhabitants ever had the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of Travelling ſo, great a way into the World.</p>
               <p>They obſerved many wonderful things in the courſe of their Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels; but they have a Notion that <hi>Mack-Leod</hi>'s Family is Equivalent to that of an Imperial Court, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the King to be only Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to him: They ſay his Lady wore ſuch a ſtrange <hi>Lowland</hi> Dreſs, that it was impoſſible for them to deſcribe it; they admired Glaſs Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows hugely, and a Looking-Glaſs to them was a prodigy; they were amazed when they ſaw Cloth Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings put upon a thick Wall of Stone
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:199743:74"/>and Lime, and condemn'd it as a thing very Vain and Superfluous.</p>
               <p>They reckon the Year, Quarter, and Month, as generally is done all <hi>Britain</hi> over. They compute the ſeveral Periods of Time by the Lives of the Proprietors and Stewards, of whoſe great Actions they have a Tradition, of which they diſcourſe with as great ſatisfaction, as any Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian reflecting on the <hi>Caeſars,</hi> or greateſt Generals in the World.</p>
               <p>They account Riding one of the greateſt pieces of Grandeur here up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, and told me with a ſtrange admiration, that <hi>Mack-Leod</hi> did not Travel on foot, as they ſuppoſed all other Men did, and that they had ſeen ſeveral Horſes kept on purpoſe by him for Riding.</p>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:199743:74"/>
               <p>One of their Number Landing in the Iſle of <hi>Harries,</hi> enquired who was the Proprietor of thoſe Lands? They told him, that it was <hi>Mack-Leod,</hi> which did not a little raiſe his Opinion of him; this Man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, when he was in the Iſle of <hi>Sky,</hi> and had Travelled ſome Miles there, one Day ſtanding upon an Eminence, and looking round about him, he fancied he ſaw a great part of the World, and then enquired to whom thoſe Lands did belong, and when one of the Company had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted him, that <hi>Mack-Leod</hi> was Maſter of thoſe Lands alſo, the St. <hi>Kilda</hi> Man lifting up his Eyes and Hands to Heaven, cried out with admiration, <hi>O Mighty Prine, who art Maſter of ſuch Vaſt Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries!</hi> This he expreſs'd ſo emphati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Language, that the Saying from that time became a
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:199743:75"/>Proverb whenever any body would expreſs a Greatneſs and Plenitude of Power.</p>
               <p>One of the things they wondred moſt at, was the growth of Trees; they thought the Beauty of the Leaves and Branches admirable, and how they grew to ſuch a height above Plants, was far above their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception: One of them marvelling at it, told me, That the Trees pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him back as he Travelled through the Woods: They reſolved once to carry ſome few of them on their Backs to their Boats, and ſo to take them to St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> but upon ſecond thoughts, the length of the Journy, being through the greateſt part of the Iſle of <hi>Sky,</hi> deterr'd them from this undertaking, for though they excell others in Strength, yet they are very bad Travellers on foot, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but little uſed to it.</p>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:199743:75"/>
               <p>One of their Number having Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled in the Iſle of <hi>Sky,</hi> to the <hi>South</hi> part of it, thought this a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious Journy; and ſeeing in the oppoſite Continent the Shire of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneſs,</hi> divided from <hi>Sky</hi> only by a narrow Sea, enquired of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, if that was the Border of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One of the St. <hi>Kilda</hi> Men, after he had taken a pretty large Doſe of <hi>Aqua-Vitae,</hi> and was become very heavy with it, as he was falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Sleep, and fancying it was to have been his laſt, expreſs'd to his Companions the great ſatisfaction he had in meeting with ſuch an eaſy paſſage out of this World; <hi>For,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>it is attended with no kind of Pain.</hi> In ſhort, their Opinion of Foreign Objects is as remote from the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Sentiments of other Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:199743:76"/>as they are themſelves from all Foreign Converſe.</p>
               <p>I muſt not omit acquainting the Reader, that the Account given of the Seamens Rudeneſs to the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, has created great prejudices in them againſt Seamen in general; and though I endeavoured to bring them into ſome good Opinion of them, it will not be, I hope, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper here to deliver the Terms upon which the Inhabitants are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to receive Strangers, and no otherwiſe; They will not admit of any Number, exceeding Ten, and thoſe too muſt be Unarmed, for elſe the Inhabitants will oppoſe them with all their might; but if any Number of them, not exceeding that aboveſaid, come Peaceably, and with good deſigns, they may expect Water and Fire <hi>Gratis,</hi> and what elſe
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:199743:76"/>the place affords, at the eaſieſt rates in the World.</p>
               <p>The Inhabitants of St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> are much, happier than the generality of Mankind, as being almoſt the only People in the World who feel the ſweetneſs of true Liberty: What the Condition of the People in the Golden Age is feign'd by the Poets to be, that theirs really is, I mean, in Innocency and Simplicity, Purity, Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Love and Cordial Friendſhip, free from ſolicitous Cares, and anxious Covetouſneſs; from Envy, Deceit, and Diſſimulation; from Ambition and Pride, and the Conſequences that attend them. They are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ignorant of the Vices of Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners, and governed by the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of Reaſon and Chriſtianity, as it was firſt delivered to them by thoſe Heroick Souls whoſe Zeal moved them to undergo danger and
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:199743:77"/>trouble to plant Religion here in one of the remoteſt Corners of the World.</p>
               <p>There is this only wanting to make them the Happieſt People in this Habitable Globe, <hi>viz.</hi> That they themſelves do not know how happy they are, and how much they are above the Avarice and Slavery of the reſt of Mankind. Their way of living makes them contemn Gold and Silver, as below the Dignity of Human Nature; they live by the Munificence of Heaven, and have no Deſigns upon one another, but ſuch as are purely ſuggeſted by Juſtice and Benevolence.</p>
               <p>There being about Thirty of the Inhabitants one Day together in the Iſle <hi>Soa,</hi> they eſpied a Man with a Grey Coat and Plad, in a Shirt, floating on the Sea upon his Belly, and ſaw likewiſe a <hi>Mall</hi> pecking at
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:199743:77"/>his Neck; this Viſion continued above a Quarter of an Hour, and then diſappeared; but ſhortly after, one of the Spectators chanc'd to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sea, and being Drowned, reſembled the forewarning Viſion in all things, and the <hi>Mall</hi> was alſo ſeen upon his Neck; this was told me by the Steward ſome Years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and afterwards was confirmed to me by ſuch as were themſelves Eye-witneſſes of it.</p>
               <p>None of the Inhabitants pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the <hi>Second Sight,</hi> except <hi>Roderick</hi> the Impoſtor, and one Woman, and ſhe told her Neighbours that ſhe ſaw, ſome Weeks before our coming, a Boat (different from that of the Steward) with ſome Strangers in it, drawing near to their Iſle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:199743:78"/>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:199743:78"/>
               <head>An Account of one <hi>Roderick,</hi> ſuppoſed to have bad Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation with a Familiar Spirit, and pretending to be Sent by St. <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> with New Revelations and Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries.</head>
               <p>AFTER our Landing, the Miniſter and I (according to our firſt reſolution) examined the Inhabitants apart by themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the New pretended Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion delivered to them by their Falſe Prophet.</p>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:199743:79"/>
               <p>All of them, Young as well as Old, both Men and Women, una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly agreed in this following Account; They did heartily Congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulate the Miniſter's Arrival, and at the ſame time declared their Abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the Impoſtor's Deluſions, and with repeated Inſtances begg'd for the Lord's ſake that he might be for ever removed out of the Iſle.</p>
               <p>This Impoſtor is a Comely well-proportioned Fellow, Red-hair'd, and exceeding all the Inhabitants of St. <hi>Kilda</hi> in Strength, Climbing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He is Illiterate, and under the ſame circumſtances with his Companions, for he had not ſo much as the Advantage of ever ſeeing any of the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Iſles; all his Converſe being only with the Steward's Reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, who were as ignorant of Letters as himſelf.</p>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:199743:79"/>
               <p>In the Eighteenth Year of his Age, he took the Liberty of going to Fiſh on a <hi>Sunday,</hi> (a practice altogether unknown in St. <hi>Kilda</hi>); and he aſſerts, That in his return homeward, a Man in <hi>Lowland</hi> Dreſs, <hi>i. e.</hi> a Cloak and Hat, appeared to him upon the Road; at this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected Meeting, <hi>Roderick</hi> falls flat on the Ground in great diſorder; upon which this Man deſired him not to be ſurprized at his Preſence, for he was <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately come from Heaven with good Tidings to the Inhabitants of that place, who had been for a long time kept in Ignorance and Error; that he had Commiſſion to Inſtruct <hi>Roderick</hi> in the Laws of Heaven for the Edification of his Neighbours: <hi>Roderick</hi> anſwered, That he was no way qualified for ſo great a Charge; the pretended <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> deſired
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:199743:80"/>him to be of good Courage, for he would inſtantly make him capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for his Miſſion, and then deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to him the following Scheme, in which he ſo mixed the lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Cuſtoms of the Church with his own Diabolical Inventions, that it became impoſſible for ſo Ignorant a People as they, to diſtinguiſh the one from the other.</p>
               <p>The Firſt and Principal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand which be impoſed upon them, was that of the <hi>Friday's</hi> Faſt, which he enjoined to be obſerved with ſuch ſtrictneſs, as not to allow one of them to taſte any kind of Food before Night, no, not ſo much as a Snuff of Tobacco, which they love dearly; this bare Faſt, without any Religious Exerciſe attending it, was the firſt Badge and Cognizance of his Followers. He perſuaded the People, that ſome of their Deceaſed
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:199743:80"/>Neighbours were Nominated Saints in Heaven, and Advocates for them here who ſurviv'd; he told, every one had his reſpective Advocate; the Anniverſary of every Saint was to be commemorated by every Perſon under whoſe Tutelage they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to be. And this was obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Treating the Neighbours with a liberal Entertainment of Beef or Mutton, Fowls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Impoſtor himſelf being always the chief Gueſt at the Feaſt; where a Share of the Entertainment was punctually ſent to his Wife and Children; the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Sheep ordinarily conſumed on theſe occaſions, was proportionable to the Ability of him that beſtowed them.</p>
               <p>He impoſed likewiſe ſeveral Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances which they were obliged to ſubmit to, under the pain of being expelled from the Society of his Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:199743:81"/>in Worſhip, which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be founded upon no leſs Authority than that of St. <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt's,</hi> and threatned to inflict the ſaddeſt Judgments upon thoſe as ſhould prove Refractory, and not obey his Injunctions.</p>
               <p>The ordinary Penances he laid upon them, were to make them ſtand in Cold Water (without regard to the Seaſon, whether Froſt or otherwiſe) during his pleaſure; and if there were any more of them upon whom this Severity was to be Inflicted, they were to pour Cold Water up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one another's Heads until they had ſatisfied his Tyrannical Humour. This Diabolical Severity was Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence enough, that he was ſent by him who is the <hi>Father of Lies, and was a Murtherer from the beginning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He commanded that every Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily ſhould Slay a Sheep upon the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:199743:81"/>Threſhold of their Doors, but a Knife muſt not ſo much as touch it, he would have them only make uſe of their Crooked Spades for their Inſtruments to Kill them with; for which, if duly conſidered, there is nothing more improper, the Edge with which he commanded the Sheep's Neck to be cut being almoſt Half an Inch thick. Now this was to be done in the Evening, and if either Young or Old had Taſted a bit of the Meat of it that Night, the equivalent Number of Sheep were to be ſlain the following Day, after the former manner.</p>
               <p>He forbid the uſe of the Lord's Prayer, Creed, and Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and inſtead of them pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Diabolical Forms of his Own. His Prayers and Rhapſodical Forms were often blended with the Names of God, our Bleſſed Saviour, and the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:199743:82"/>Immaculate Virgin; he uſed the <hi>Iriſh</hi> word <hi>Pherſichin, i. e.</hi> Verſes, which is not known in St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> nor in the <hi>North-Weſt</hi> Iſles, except to ſuch as can Read the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Tongue. But that which ſeems to be moſt ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, in his obſcure Prayers, was his mentioning <hi>ELI,</hi> with the Character of our Preſerver. He uſed ſeveral unintelligible Words in his Prayers, of which he could not tell the meaning himſelf; ſaying only, That he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived them implicitly from St. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> and delivered them before his Hearers without any Explication.</p>
               <p>He Taught the Women a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Hymn, which he called the <hi>Virgin Mary's,</hi> as ſent from her; this Hymn was never delivered in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, but always in a private Houſe, or ſome remote place where no Eye could ſee them but that of Heaven; he perſuaded the Innocent Women
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:199743:82"/>that it was of ſuch Merit and Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy, that any one who was able to repeat it by heart, would not Die in Child-bearing: And every Woman paid a Sheep to the Impoſtor for Teaching her this Hymn.</p>
               <p>The Place and Manner of Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Hymn afforded him a fair opportunity of Debauching the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Women; and this ſome of their number acknowledged to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and me upon Examination.</p>
               <p>He preſcribed to all his Auditory, long Rhimes, which he called Pſalms; theſe he ordinarily Sung at his Rhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſodical Preachments.</p>
               <p>He endeavoured to alter the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon way of Burying, which was by placing the Faces of the Dead to the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and would have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded them to place them to the <hi>South,</hi> and that he might prevail the more with them ſo to do, he placed
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:199743:83"/>the Bodies of thoſe of his own Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily who happened to Die, facing the <hi>South;</hi> yet the Inhabitants would not follow his Example in this, but continued in their former Practice.</p>
               <p>He perſuaded the Women, That if in all things they complied with his New Revelation, they ſhould be undoubtedly carried to Heaven, and that in their Journy thither they were to paſs through the Firmament Riding upon White Horſes. Theſe and many more Ridiculous things he impoſed upon the People, of which this is but an Abſtract.</p>
               <p>This unhappy Fellow to conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate his Enterprize, pitched upon a little riſing ſpot of Ground, which he called <hi>John the Baptiſt's Buſh;</hi> upon which he ſaid theſe Oracles were delivered by <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> to him. And this Buſh was from that time forward
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:199743:83"/>believed to be Holy Ground, and muſt not be any further Trod up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by any of their Cattel, and if by chance one of them happen to touch it, it muſt be forthwith ſlain and eaten by <hi>Roderick</hi> and the Own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; and if any proved refractory, and were reſolved to ſpare their Cattel, a moſt dreadful Commination was iſſued out againſt them, or being thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward excluded from any further Fellowſhip with him, until they ſhould acknowledge their Faults, and comply with his Luxurious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, which to diſobey he made them believe was Damnable. It was reckoned Meritorious if any body had revealed who had Tranſgreſſed the Orders given by him.</p>
               <p>This Impoſtor continued for the ſpace of ſeveral Years, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul, to delude theſe poor innocent well-meaning People, until at laſt
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:199743:84"/>his Villanous Deſign upon the Women was found out, I mean, That he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to accompliſh under the Mask of the Devout Hymn that he Taught them, and was firſt diſcovered by the Officer's Wife, who by the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor was firſt proſelited to his Falſe Doctrines, and after that he would have Debauched her from her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugal Fidelity. This Woman was ſo Heroically. Virtuous, as to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate his lewd Deſign to her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, who ordered the matter ſo as to be in another Room hard by at the ſame time he ſuppoſed <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick</hi> would be coming; there he ſtays until this Letcher began to careſs his Wife, and then he thought himſelf obliged ſeaſonably to appear for her reſcue, and boldly reproved the Impoſtor for his wicked practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which were ſo widely contrary to his Profeſſion, and that upon
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:199743:84"/>the whole it appeared he had no true Miſſion.</p>
               <p>The Impoſtor was very much ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized at this unexpected and fatal diſappointment, which put him into an extream diſorder, inſomuch that he asked the Officer's Pardon, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging his Crime, and promiſing never to attempt the like again. The Officer continued to upbraid him, telling him to his face, That he was ſet on by the Devil; that Innocence and Chaſtity were always the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of True Religion, and that the contrary practices were countenanced by Falſe Prophets; and that now they needed no other proof of his being a Notorious Deceiver: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Impoſtor being had in great Reputation, prevailed with the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer to patch up a Friendſhip with him, who for the continuance of it, condeſcended to be the Impoſtor's
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:199743:85"/>
                  <hi>Goſſip, i. e.</hi> Sponſor at the Baptiſm of one of his Children; of which Ceremony there is an account al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready given: When there is no op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of being Sponſor to one another, and it is neceſſary to enter into Bonds of Friendſhip at Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm; the Inhabitants of the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Iſles, ſupplied this Ceremony by Taſting a drop of each other's Blood.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding this Friendſhip thus patch'd up between theſe Two, the Impoſtor's miſcarriages got Air, which adminiſtred occaſion to the moſt thinking among them, to doubt very much of his Miſſion; his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who was reputed a very Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Man, told him frequently, that he was a Deceiver, and would come to a fatal end. This Impoſtor Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied that one of the Inhabitants
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:199743:85"/>(whoſe Name I have forgotten) was to be Killed in a Battel which was to be fought in the Iſle of <hi>Harries,</hi> within a limited ſpace of time; this poor unthinking Man relying ſo much on one whom he thought an infallible Oracle, ventured more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately on the Rock than ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, fancying he could not fall, but it happened that he tumbled over and was Drowned, at which the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants were ſurprized; however the Impoſtor continued in the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of his pretended Miſſion.</p>
               <p>One of the Inhabitants called <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donich,</hi> alias <hi>Lewis,</hi> Couſin-German to the Impoſtor, had an Ewe which brought forth Three Lambs at once, they were ſeen to feed upon the Buſh pretended to be Sacred, but <hi>Lewis</hi> would not comply with the Order for Killing the Sheep, and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:199743:86"/>had the boldneſs to aver, That it was an unreaſonable piece of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to deſtroy ſo many Cattel, and deprive the Owners of their uſe, adding withal, That he never heard any ſuch thing practiſed in any of the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Iſles upon a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious account. The Impoſtor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted upon the Heavenly Command, which was to be obſerved by all his Followers, adding the dreadful Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning againſt ſuch as proved diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient thereto; but <hi>Lewis</hi> would by no means be prevailed upon, chuſing rather to be excluded from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Worſhip, than to Kill his Sheep.</p>
               <p>The ſimple People looked for no leſs than a ſpeedy Judgment to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall this Recuſant, but when nothing enſued upon his Diſobedience, all of them began to have a leſs Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the Impoſtor than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore;
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:199743:86"/>nay, ſome ſaid privately, that they might as well have ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured to run the ſame riſque with <hi>Lewis,</hi> for the preſervation of their Cattel.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding all this Villany, the Impoſtor continued to maintain his Authority, until one Night (for it was always at Night that he kept his pretended Religious Meetings) by a ſpecial Providence, a Boy of the Iſle of <hi>Harries,</hi> called <hi>John</hi> (who had ſtaid with his Father a Year in St. <hi>Kilda,</hi> and was employed in mending of their Boat) happened to go into the Houſe where <hi>Roderick</hi> was preaching after his uſual man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; the Boy lurked in the dark, and gave his Father an account of what he had heard, ſo far as he could remember; all which the Boy's Father communicated to the Steward upon his Arrival, who being highly
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:199743:87"/>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned at the Relation given him, carried <hi>Roderick</hi> along with him to the Iſle of <hi>Sky</hi> before the late <hi>Mack-Leod,</hi> who being informed of this Fellow's Impoſtures, did forbid him from that time forward to Preach any more on pain of Death.</p>
               <p>This was a great mortification, as well as diſappointment to the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor, who was poſſeſſed with a fancy, that <hi>Mack-Leod</hi> would hear him Preach, and expected no leſs than to perſuade him to become one of his Proſelytes, as he has ſince confeſſed.</p>
               <p>The Impoſtor aſſerts, That every Night after he had aſſembled the People, he heard a Voice without, ſaying, <hi>Come you out;</hi> which when he heard, he had no power to ſtay within; and that after his going forth, <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> did meet him, and Inſtructed him what he ſhould
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:199743:87"/>ſay to the People at that particular meeting. He ſays, That <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> uſed only to repeat the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to him once, of all which the Impoſtor owns he could ſcarcely remember one Sentence, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he enquired of <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> how he ſhould behave himſelf in this caſe; and that <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> returned this anſwer, <hi>Go, you have it;</hi> which the Impoſtor believing, was upon his return able to deliver flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently all that he had heard, and would continue (after this his way of Preaching) for ſeveral Hours together, until he had lull'd moſt of his Hearers aſleep.</p>
               <p>When the above-mentioned Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake was over, one of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants enquired of the Impoſtor with admiration, How the Rock was made to tremble? He anſwered, That it was the effect of pleaſant Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:199743:88"/>ſick played by a Devout Saint in a Church under ground: His Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour owned his love for Muſick, but heartily wiſhed never to hear any more of this kind, which carried ſo great terror along with it.</p>
               <p>The Impoſtor owned the truth of all this Account, firſt to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and me, and then he did the ſame publickly after Divine Service, in the preſence of all the Inhabitants, and ſuch as were come to that place from the Iſle of <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</hi> The Miniſter and Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion jointly prayed for Repentance and Pardon to this poor Wretch, which when ended, we carried him and all the Inhabitants to the Buſh pretended to be Sacred; he himſelf leading the Van, was commanded to Raze to the Ground a part of that Wall which he had ordered to
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:199743:88"/>be built round the ſaid Buſh (which otherwiſe would in a ſhort time have proved ſuch a Purgatory, as might have robb'd them of all their Goods) which he and the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants did in the ſpace of an Hour; we made them ſcatter the Stones up and down in the Field, leſt their Poſterity might ſee ſuch a Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Folly and Ignorance. We Reproved the Credulous People for complying implicitly with ſuch Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and Deluſions as were delivered to them by the Impoſtor; and all of them with once Voice anſwered, That what they did was Unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable; but ſeeing one of their own number and ſtamp in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, endued, as they fancied, with a powerful faculty of Preaching ſo fluently and frequently, and pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Converſe with <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> they were induc'd to believe his
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:199743:89"/>Miſſion from Heaven, and therefore complied with his Commands with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſpute, and the rather, becauſe he did not change their Laws of Neighbourhood.</p>
               <p>They do now regret their wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, and hope that God may pardon their Error, ſince what they did was with a deſign (though a miſtaken one) to ſerve him.</p>
               <p>They are now overjoyed to find themſelves undeceived, and the Light of the Goſpel reſtored to them, as it was at firſt delivered to their Anceſtors by the firſt Chriſtian Monks, who had gone thither to Inſtruct them.</p>
               <p>This Impoſtor is a Poet, and alſo endued with that rare Faculty of enjoying the <hi>Second Sight,</hi> which
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:199743:89"/>makes it the more probable that he was haunted by a Familiar Spirit. It hath been obſerved of him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Impoſture was diſcovered, that ſo often as he was employed by the Steward to go to, or return from <hi>Harries,</hi> they were always ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the greateſt Dangers by violent Storms, being at one time driven Fifty Leagues to the <hi>North-Eaſt,</hi> and by ſpecial Providence were at laſt caſt upon the little Iſle <hi>Rona,</hi> Twenty Leagues <hi>North-Eaſt</hi> of <hi>Lewis;</hi> the Steward's Wife, and all his Crew making their reflections upon theſe Dangers ſince the diſcovery of his Impoſture, could never be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed upon to receive him again into their Boat. They often in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated Mr. <hi>Campbell</hi> and me not to admit him into our Boat, but we did not yield to theſe Fears, for we received and brought him along
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:199743:90"/>with us, and afterwards delivered him to the Steward's Servants in the Iſle of <hi>Pabby</hi> in <hi>Harries,</hi> where he remains ſtill in Cuſtody in order to his Trial.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 13. <hi>line</hi> 3. <hi>for</hi> tripple <hi>read</hi> treble. <hi>l.</hi> 12. <hi>for</hi> Vilage <hi>r.</hi> Village. <hi>p.</hi> 14. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>for</hi> heather <hi>r.</hi> heath. <hi>p.</hi> 48. <hi>for</hi> his <hi>r.</hi> its, <hi>for</hi> he <hi>r.</hi> it. <hi>p.</hi> 49. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>for</hi> he <hi>r.</hi> it. <hi>p.</hi> 56, <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>for</hi> his <hi>r.</hi> it <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>and</hi> 8. <hi>for</hi> he <hi>r.</hi> it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:199743:90"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed for</hi> Dan. Brown <hi>at the</hi> Black Swan <hi>and</hi> Bible <hi>without</hi> Temble-Bar.</head>
            <p>A Treatiſe of the Gout, wherein both its Cauſe and Cure are demonſtrably made appear; to which is added ſome Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinal Obſervations concerning the Cure of Fevers by the means of <hi>Acids.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Doctrine of <hi>Acids</hi> in the Cure of Diſeaſes further Aſſerted, being an Anſwer to Dr. <hi>F. Tuthill,</hi> &amp;c. In which are contained ſome things relating to the Hiſtory of Blood, as alſo an Attempt to prove what Life is, and that it is principally ſupported by <hi>Acid</hi> and <hi>Sulpher,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <div type="publishers_note__cont.">
               <head>Both by <hi>J. Colbach,</hi> a Member of the College of Phyſicians.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Curſus Oſteologicus:</hi> Being a Compleat Doctrine of the Bones, according to the Neweſt and moſt refined Notions of Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>Robert Baker,</hi> Chirurgeon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Gentlemans Recreation, in Four Parts, viz.</hi> Hunting, Hawking, Fowling, Fiſhing; wherein theſe generous Exerciſes are largely Treated of, and the Terms of Art for Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Hawking more amply enlarged than heretofore; alſo the method and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Breeding and Managing a Hunting-Horſe; with Sculptures inſerted proper to each Recreation: <hi>The Fourth Edition.</hi> To which is now added a perfect Abſtract of all the Foreſt Laws to this time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="publishers_note__cont.">
               <pb facs="tcp:199743:91"/>
               <head>Books <hi>Printed for</hi> Timothy Goodwin.</head>
               <p>A Political Eſſay: Or, Summary Review of the Kings and Government of <hi>England</hi> ſince the <hi>Norman</hi> Conqueſt. By <hi>W</hi>— <hi>P</hi>—<hi>ey</hi>
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr>.</p>
               <p>An Account of <hi>Poland,</hi> containing a Geogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical Deſcription of the Country; the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Inhabitants, and the Wars they have been engaged in; the Conſtitution of that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, particularly the manner of Electing and Crowning their Kings, his Power and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative; with a brief Hiſtory of the <hi>Tartars.</hi> By Monſieur <hi>Hautevile,</hi> who Reſided about Twenty five Years in that Kingdom. To which is added a Chronology of the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Kings, the Abdication of King <hi>John Caſimir,</hi> and the riſe and progreſs of <hi>Socinianiſm;</hi> likewiſe a Relation of the chief Paſſages during the late <hi>Inter-regnum,</hi> and the Election and Coronation of the New King <hi>Frederic Auguſtus.</hi> The whole comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whatſoever is Curious and worthy of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark in the former and preſent State of <hi>Poland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lex Parliamentaria:</hi> Or, a Treatiſe of the Law and Cuſtoms of the Parliaments of <hi>England.</hi> By <hi>G. P.</hi>
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Politica Sacra &amp; Civilis:</hi> Or, a Model of Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Government; wherein beſides the poſitive Doctrine concerning State and Church in general, are debated, the principal Controverſies of the times concerning the Conſtitution of the State and Church of <hi>England,</hi> tending to Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, Truth, and Peace. By <hi>George Lawſon,</hi> Rector of <hi>More</hi> in the County of <hi>Salop.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Account of <hi>Denmark</hi> as it was in the Year 1692. <hi>Third Edition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Account of <hi>Sueden,</hi> together with an Extract of the Hiſtory of that Kingdom.</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:199743:91"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
